<review>

<heparin>
PTT control is 38 seconds, theraputic should be 1.5 - 2.5 x control
Petechia on chest is an adverse effect
</heparin>

<phlebitis>
Discontinue infusion and apply a warm soak, document
No need to contact the prescriber
</phlebitis>

<transfusion>
Blood should be transfused within 2-4 hours
Needle guage should be 18-20G to insure that cells aren't damaged
Monitor clients for first 15 min then periodically after 
</transfusion>

<urine>
Normal out put is 800 to 2000 mL/day ()
</urine>

<benzodiazepines>
Don't ambulate clients after administering a benzo, even to the bathroom
Don't administer an opiod after, due to risk of respiratory depression
</benzodiazepines>


<preoperative>
teaching about the procedure and experience, taching about pain and pain relief, controling client's anxiety, basic needs like elimination are met, maintain NPO status
Alert the anesthesiologist of any PO meds given prior 
</preoperative>

<multiple-sclerosis>
treatment is with beta interferon
</multiple-sclerosis>

<parkinson>
Early symptoms: fatigue, loss of smell
</parkinson>

<dialysis>
Administering an antihypertensive prior to could lead to hypotension, the nurse should wait until after dialysis to administer it.
Antimicrobials and antibiotics are removed with the dialysate solution, should be withheld until after. 
</dialysis>

<influenza>
FDA approved antivirals: peramivir, zanamivir, oseltamivir, baloxavir
Antivirals decrease the efficacy of the vaccine
</influenza>

<glasgow-coma-scale>
Assesses three areas of conciousness - verbal response, motor response, eye opening
Maximum score is 15, minimal score is 3
Eyes open (1-4): none, to pain, to speech, spontaneously
Verbal (1-5): none, incomprehensible, inappropriate, confused, oriented
Motor (1-6): none, abnormal extension, abnormal flexion, withdrawl, localizes pain, obeys commands
</glasgow-coma-scale>

<ascites>
Abdominal skin is taut and glistening
</ascites>

<bladder-distension>
Dull percussion over symphisis pubis
</bladder-distension>

<sickle-cell-crisis>
Fluids are used to reduce blood viscosity
Activity is limited to reduce oxygen needs
Diet is used to promote metabolic demand, rich in calories and high in protein
Oxygen is atministed to prevent further cell sickling
Pain management should be done with a combination of opiod and nonopiod drugs, not just nonopioid, as pain could be severe
</sickle-cell-crisis>

<low-molecular-weight-heparin>
aPTT is not used to monitor them, no frequent blood tests are required
Given to prevent lower limb blood clots
Lower risk of bleeding than heparin, but the risk is still present
</low-molecular-weight-heparin>

<LPN-duties>
All clients must be stable and require ruoutine, unchaning procedures, they cannot care for clients who require assessments 
Colostomy care
Administering oral meds
</LPN-duties>

<potassium>
Low - flattened T waves, prominent U waves, ST-segment depression, prolonged PR interval, 
</potassium>

<para-thyroid-hormone>
Primary target is the kidney and bone
Causes blood levels of calcium to rise 
Causes calcium conservation in the kidney
</para-thyroid-hormone>

<calcium>
Bound with fatty acids
</calcium>

<nsaid>
Increase blood pressure, counterindicated in individuals with hypertension
Affect platelet clotting, increase the risk of bleeding especially with 
</nsaid>

<cholelithiasis>
Risk factors include Native American and Hispanic origins, obesity, multiparousness, age over 40, fasting
</cholelithiasis>

<alcohol-withdrawal>
Signs and symptoms: elevated temperature, nocturnal leg cramps, generalized muscle pain and malaise, tremors
</alcohol-withdrawal>

<ibuprofen>
Maximum daliy dosage: 3,200 mg/day
</ibuprofen>

<statin>
Must be given at night when cholesterol production is highest
</statin>

<hemolytic-transfusion-reaction>
Symptoms: chills, low back/chest pain, hypotension, tachycardia
Treatment: stop the transfusion, obtain a urine specime, maintain blood volume and renal perfusion with an IV colloid solution (like albumin, gelatin, dextran, starch).
</hemolytic-transfusion-reaction>

<febrile-transfusion-reaction>
Temperature increase > 1 degree Celsius
Headache
Nausea/vomiting
</febrile-transfusion-reaction>

<who-do-you-see-first-rules>
Is the client stable or unstable? Eliminate stable clients.
Is the client experiencing expected or unexpeced findings? Eliminate expecting findgins. 
Are the reminaing answers referring to airway, breathing or circulation (ABCs)? Eliminate each non-priority answer option using the ABCs.
Are the reminaing asnwer options real (actual) or potential problems? Eliminate the potential problem answer options.
</who-do-you-see-first-rules>

<systemic-lupus-erythematosus>
Malar rash - rash extending across the nasal bridge and upper cheeks.
</systemic-lupus-erythematosus>

<chronic-kidney-disease>
Foods to avoid: citrus fruit, they are high in potassium as damaged kidneys cannot remove it. 
Dried fruits, avocado, tomato, potatoes and bananas. 
Calcium is lost through the damaged kidneys.
Dairy products are high in phosphorus which binds even more calcium and should be avoided.
Dietary protein incrases uric acid (urea) production which cannot be cleared by the damaged kidneys. Dietary protein should be kept at low or normal levels (but not incrased).
</chronic-kidney-disease>

<right-sided-heart-failure>
Congestion of the gastric veins, resulting in anorexia and eventual development of ascites
</right-sided-heart-failure>

<lithium-toxicity>
Early signs: nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, tremors and twitching. 
Late signs: fever, ataxia, confusion, and seizures.
</lithium-toxicity>

<fluid-intake>
Normal fluid intake should be between 1,500 - 2,000 ml/day
</fluid-intake>

<skin-grafting>
Priority should be given to grafit immobilization, since the graft must adhere to the site for vascularization to take place. It takes between 7-10 days to adhere. 
</skin-grafting>

<low-hemoglobin>
First apply oxygen to make sure the available hemoglobin is well oxygenated, place on cariac monitor, start the intravenous catheter, draw the blood work.
</low-hemoglobin>

<hyperkalemia>
Elevated T-waves
</hyperkalemia>

<cushing-disease>
Overproduction of corticosteroids, mainly cortisol or hypercortisolism. 
Cortisol is associated with an incrase in glucose levels, increased sodium levels, decreased potassium and calcium levels. 
</cushing-disease>

<corticosteroid>
Increases levels of glucose, increases sodium levels, decreases potassium and calcium levels
</corticosteroid>


<liver-failure>
Underproduction of bicarbonate leads to metabolic-acidosis 
</liver-failure>

<ascites>
Pushes on the lungs, decreasing lung capacity
</ascites>

<acidosis>
Associated with hyperkalemia
</acidosis>

<hyperkalemia> 
Treatment is to administer insulin, insulin activates sodium-proton pump which pumps sodium ions in to the cell and hydrogen ions out, the influx of sodium activates the the sodium-potassium pump which job it's to maintain intracellular potassium concentrations higher and sodium concentrations lower. The Na-K pump exports 3 ions of sodium and imports two ions of potassium, lowering the overall serum potassium concentration.
Symptom is an elevated T wave
</hyperkalemia> 

<fetal-kick-counting>
Must be done the same time each day, preferrably after a meal in the left side lying position.
Should not be less then 10 kicks in 2 hours, or less then 3 kickins in one hour.
If the test fails, then a non-stress test should be performed. 
</fetal-kick-counting>

<above-knee-amputation>
Compression dressing should be maintained to minimize edema, prevent infection and shape the stubb. 
Elevate the amputated limb for 24 hours after surgery. 
Range of motion excercises every 2-4 hours.
No sitting in chair for prolonged times to prevent hip flexion contractions.
</above-knee-amputation>

<milieu-therapy>
Intended to treat behaviour and personality disorders. All aspects of the environemnt are utilized to alter the behaviour and personality. Each member is assigned a set of responsibilities and activities that allow them to develop healthy social behaviours. 
Keys to successful therapy: support, structure, repetition, consistent expectations.
</milieu-therapy>

<alzheimer>
Reduced anxiety first then reorient the client. 
Reduce anxiety by staying with the client and explaining the environment. 
Clients may be calmer in the morning and get more agitated as the day progresses. 
</alzheimer>

<hepatitis-a>
Spread via fecal-oral route.
In pediatric clients symptoms are flu like in nature, including anorexia, fever, malaise, lethargy, clay colored stools, dark urine. Jaundice is not common in pediatric patients. 
Before age 6, 70% of patients will be asymptomatic. 
</hepatitis-a>

<myxedema>
Refers to severe hypothyroidisim.
Symptoms: very cold, tired and sluggish.
</myxedema>

<poisoning>
Call Poison Control Center not 911
</poisoning>

<uterine-hyper-tonicity>
When one contractions lasts 2 minutes or longer or when there are 5 or more contractions in 10 minutes.
</uterine-hyper-tonicity>


<infant-respiratory-rate>
Less then 66 breaths per minute (normal), if greater then tachypnea
</infant-respiratory-rate>

<toilet-training>
Ready between 18 months to 3 years
Parents must have 2 weeks of free time off work.
Child must be able to sit for 5-10 minutes.
Must be able to have fine motor skills to dress and unrdress.
</toilet-training>

<pediatric-cardiac-defect>
Check child for hypoxia which is indicated by squatting after activity, cyanosis, tachycardia and sweating.
</pediatric-cardiac-defect>

<chronic-alcohol-abuse>
Hypomagnesemia - trermors, confusion, racing heart - could be dangerous is severe. 
</chronic-alcohol-abuse>

<urinary-incontinence>
Toilet schedule - voiding every 2 hours
Stress incontinence - occurs when abdominal pressure increases due to sneezing, laughter etc. 
Urge incontinence - occurs after experience sudden urge to void, with an inability to suppress urination before reaching bathroom. 
</urinary-incontinence>

<hypocalcemia>
tetany - spasms of hands, legs and feet, could also result in breating and cardio disturbances.
Chvostek sign - facial contraction when tapping on the facial nerve.
Trousseau sign - muscle scpasm of the hand and wrist when blood pressure cuff is applied.
</hypocalcemia>

<deep-vein-thrombosis>
Do not massage, promote bed rest and not moving the extremity, elevate the extremity on pillows to reduce edema and promote venous return. 
</deep-vein-thrombosis>

<tuberculosis> 
Transporting - a patient with TB should be wearing a surgical mask (not N95) and the persons caring for them should be alerted and wear N95.
</tuberculosis>

<sickle-cell-crisis>
Blood test shows increased reticulocyte (immature red blood cells) count.
Hematocrit is decreased. 
Hemoglobin level is decreased. 
Causes: hypoxemia, dehydration, infection, excessive esercise, cold temperatures.
Treatment: oxygenation, hydration, adequate rest, warmth. 
</sickle-cell-crisis>

<IV-Push>
Port nearest to the insertion site.
Tubing above should be clamped.
Use a watch with to time push duration
</IV-Push>

<scabies>
Transmission of scabies occurs through mites. 
</scabies>

<escherichia-coli>
Transmitted by fecal-oral route, causes acute diarrhea.
Standard precautions are enough unless the client is incontinetn or is diapered, then contact precautions are needed. 
</escherichia-coli>

<hepatitis-a>
Transmitted through a fecal-oral route.
Standard precautiuons are enough unless incontinent or diapered, then contact precautions are needed. 
</hepatitis-a>

<gastrostomy-tube>
Monitor prealbumin levels, it has shorter half life than albumin and is a better reflection of the patient's nutritional status.
</gastrostomy-tube>

<poly-cystic-ovarian-syndrome>
Metabolic disorder diagnosed in adolescence. Characterized by ovulatory dysfunction, amenorrhea, cysts in the ovaries, hyperandrogenism.
Most common in women under 30 and may cause infertility. 
Hormonal changes include increased testosterone, decreased progesterone and increased insulin resistance. 
Causes moood instability, stubborn weight gain, hair growth on face (hirsutism), acne. 
Women must strive to maintain normal weight, which can result in a more regular menstrual cycle. 
</poly-cystic-ovarian-syndrome>

<leadership-models>
Transformational leader - encouraging selfmotivation, and commitment
Autocratic leader - (ruler with absolute power) leader makes decision with no input from staff.
Laissez faire leader - (french for let it be) leader does not want to make decisions but lets other decide
Democratic leader - leader seeks inputs from staff before making decisions.
</leadership-models>

<neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>
Life threatening idiosynchratic reaction to dopamine receptor-antagonist drugs.
Usually occurs 4-14 days after the start of therapy. 
Symptoms: sudden high fever, rigidity, tachycardia, hypertension, decreased level of consciousness. 
Bromocriptine should be administered, it counteracts the effects of dopamine antagonists. 
</neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>

<bromocriptine>
Dopamine receptor agonist.
Reduces prolacting levels (treats hyperprolactinemia).
Treats acromegaly by decreasing the amounts of human growth hormone.
Treats Parkinson's disease. 
</bromocriptine>

<sequential-compression-devices>
Remove at least once every 8 hours.
Monitor for one full cycle after applying.
</sequential-compression-devices>

<iron-supplements>
Should be taken on empty stomach, with vitamin C enriched juice.
</iron-supplements>

<sulfonyureas>
Developed in 1950's.
Increase the release of insulin from the pancreas.
Common meds in class:
glyburide, glimepiride, glipizide
Common interactions: beta blockers - mask hypoglycemia which is the primary adverse effect of oral antidiabetic agents.
Gemfibrozil - cholesterol medication, could increase the hypoglycemic effects of sulfonyureas.
Aspirin and oral anticoagulants, MAOIs, sulfonamides (antibiotics mostly for UTI), cimetidine  - displace the sulfonyureas from the transport proteins, thereby increasing their effect
Thiazides, Isoniazid, Phenytoin, Corticosteroids - decrease the effects of sulfonyureas.
</sulfonyureas>

<ginkgo-biloba>
Can cause bleeding, taking it with other meds that cause bleeding can increase the effect. 
Thought to increase mental fitness. Studies failed to show any increase except in dimentia. 
</ginkgo-biloba>

<ginseng>
Increases the hypoglycemic effects of sulfonyureas.
Boost energy, lowers blood sugar and cholesterol, reduces stress, manages sexual dysfunction.
</ginseng>


<ibuprofen>
Increases the hypoglycemic effect of oral antidiabetics.
Increases risk of bleeding.
Increases risk of heart attack and stroke as early as a week after taking it consistently.
</ibuprofen>

<lumbar-puncture>
Food and fluids are not restricted
After procedure instruct the client to lay flat for 6-8 hours
Encourage fluids 
</lumbar-puncture>

<cancer>
Most common cancer deaths are from smoking associated lung cancer. 
Most common cancer diagnosis is from skin cancer.
</cancer>

<live-vaccines>
Measles, mumps, rubella (MMR), varicella (chicken pox), rotavirus, influenza.
Should not be given to pregnant women, vaccinate in postpartum period, because of the theoretical risk of tranmission to the fetus. 
Influenza vaccines are recommended if pregnant during the influenza season. 
</live-vaccines>

<low-back-pain>
Don't straing to reach for things.
Do not lie in prone position.
Avoid knee and hip extension.
</low-back-pain>

<meningitis>
Fever, neck pain and stiffness, Headache
</meningitis>

<basal-skull-fracture>
CNS leak from the ear
</basal-skull-fracture>

<suicide>
Ask about frequency, duration and intensity of suicidal thoughts (suicidal ideation).
Ask abou the suicide plan like the method and time and place.
Ask about prior attempts or rehersals. 
Evaluate the intent to follow through with the plan. 
Maintain a safe environment and place on constant observation. 
</suicide>

<influenza-vaccine> 
Fever is common and expected side effect, up to 39C (102.8F)
</influenza-vaccine>

<shock>
Hypovolemic, cardiogenic, obstructive, distributive (neurogenic, septic, anaphylectic).
Signs and symptoms: tachycardia, low blood pressure, palor. 
</shock>

<hyperthyroidism>
Tachycardia, intolerance to heat, polyphagia (excessive eating), nervousness and dry hair as well as hypertension. 
</hyperthyroidism>

<vena-cava-syndrome>
Aka: supine hypotensive syndrome
Reduction of cardiac output when the gravid uterus puts pressure on the vena cava, especially in the supine position.
Lying on the side, takes the pressure off the vena cava.
</vena-cava-syndrome>

<retinal-detachment>
Medical emergency.
Feels like a curtain is being pulled over eyes.
</retinal-detachment>

<meningitis>
Monitor for deterioration: decreased LOC, Cushing triad, impaired pupil reactivity to light.
</meningitis>

<cushing-triad>
Indicates increase in intracranial pressure. 
Bradycardia, irregular respirations, widened pulse pressure. 
</cushing-triad>

<play-by-age>
Infant (0-1) - solitary play, focusted on their own activity but enjoy the presence of others.
Toddler (1-3) - parallel play, playing along side but not with others.  
</play-by-age>

<mastitis>
Blocked duct due to bacterial infection, causes reddned inflamed painful breast. 
Treated with antibiotics. 
Cracked nipples.
Risk factor is poor hygine.
Failure to empty while breastfeeding. 
</mastitis>


<tricuspid-valve>
Auscultate at S1: 5th intercostal, left sternal border. 
</tricuspid-valve>

<nebulizer>
Delivers medication through water mist. 
Excessive use can cause hypervolemia due to excessive fluid absorption. 
</nebulizer>

<restraints>
Room where easily seen.
Food and water every 2 hours.
Monitor skin integrity every 30 mintues to monitor for redness. 
Toilet every 2 hours.
Range of motion for 10 min every 2 hours. 
Monitor every 15 min then every hour. 
</restraints>

<methycillin-resistant-staphylococcus-aureus>
Contact precautions.
</methycillin-resistant-staphylococcus-aureus>

<neisseria-meningitidis> 
Droplet precautions.
</neisseria-meningitidis>

<mycobacterium-tuberculosis>
Airborne precautions. 
</mycobacterium-tuberculosis>

<mean-arterial-pressure>
Should be at least 65.
MAP = (S+2D)/3; where S is the systolic pressure and D is the diastollic pressure. 
</mean-arterial-pressure>

<hypotension>
Begin fluid resuscitation with crystalloid solution of at least 30ml/kg over 30 min. 
If fluids don't work begin norepinephrine (Levophed) or dopamine.
</hypotension>

<hypothermia>
Shivering increases oxygen consumption. 
</hypothermia>

<hyperthermia> 
Give acetaminophen and apply a cooling blanket. 
</hyperthermia> 

<extravasation>
Happen when caustic IV solution leaks outside of the blood vessel and irritates the tissue. 
Symptoms include pain, burning and edema around the IV site.
</extravasation>

<infiltration>
Happens when non caustic IV solution leaks outside of the blood vessel. 
</infiltration>

<skin-patch>
Heat greatly increases medicine absoprtion and could result in an overdose. 
</skin-patch>

<aminophylline>
Interacts with propranolol, decreasing the bodies ability to metaboloize it leading to toxicity.
</aminophylline>

<monoamine-oxidase-inhibitors>
Avoid tyramine
Common medications in this class: isocarboxazid. 
</monoamine-oxidase-inhibitors>

<renal-calculi>
To prevent, ingest between 2,500 - 3,000 mL of fluid per day. 
</renal-calculi>

<magnetic-resonsnace-imaging>
Presence of anyurism clips is contraindicated as they could be made from a ferromagnetic material. 
</magnetic-resonsnace-imaging>

<brachytherapy>
Surgical placement of irradiated beads near the tumor. 
All treatments should be clustered together as to not come into the patient's room too many times. 
Pregnant women and children should avoid contact with the patient.
Other visitors are allowed after 24 post insertion, visits must be limited to 30 min.
</brachytherapy>

<walker>
Lift the walker, don't slide it, 8-10 inches ahead.
</walker>

<alcohol-withdrawal>
Symptoms occur 4-6 hours after last drink and last up to 14 days.
Treatment is to use benzodiazepines to alleviate the agitation. 
Common benzodiazapeine to use is chlordiazepoxide. 
Symtpoms - tremor, insomnia, dilated pupils, tachycardia, perspiration, hallucinations.
</alcohol-withdrawal>

<cardiac-temponade>

</cardiac-temponade>



<hypocalcemia>
Muscle cramps, Chvostek sign (facial nerve spasm), Trousseaue's sign (bp cuff dorsiflexion)
</hypocalcemia>

<hypercalcemia>
Weakness, nausea, polyurea  
</hypercalcemia>

<restraints>
Before applying restraints check for co-occuring medical conditions that may contraindicate their use such as vomiting or seizures. 
</restraints>

<trigeminal-nerve>
Sensation of touch on face
Controlling muscles needed to chew
</trigeminal-nerve>

<Alzheimers>
Restlessness and pacing
</Alzheimers>

<cessarian-section>
Legs could be numb from local anesthetic, which is a normal finding.
</cessarian-section>

<myasthenia-gravis>
Corticosteroids are often a part of the treatment schedule.
</myasthenia-gravis>

<incident-report>
Should be completed when the staff or clients are subject to danger, such as wrong medication, complications from procedures like extravasation, breask in asceptic technique, client refuses treatment, client voices dissatisfaction with care that cannot be resolved. 
Does not go into the client record, used for management purposes. 
</incident-report>

<chronic-kidney-disease>
Diet includes increased calories, animal protein (not plant), low potassium, low phosphorus and low sodium, limit dairy to 1 cup of milk or 1 ounce of cheese per day (because of phosphorus limits)
</chronic-kidney-disease>

<potassium-rich-foods>
Beets, oranges, melons, tomatoes, dried beans, cooked greens
</potassium-rich-foods>

<phosphorus-rich-foods>
Dairy products
Wheat cereals, oatmeal, bran and granola 
</phosphorus-rich-foods>

<suicide-assessment>
Intent to Die - how serious a patient is in carrying through
Severity of ideation - how persistent are the thoughts
Degree of planning 
</suicide-assessment>

<cephalohematoma>
Does not cross suture lines
</cephalohematoma>

<systemic-inflammatory-response-syndrome>
Caused by mechanical tissue trauma and tissue ischemia, could lead to multi organ Failure
Release of inflammatory markers, activation of coagulation cascade, decreased perfusion and hypotension
</systemic-inflammatory-response-syndrome>

<anorexia-nervosa>
Refusal to eat for the fear of gaining weight
Increased BUN due to lower blood volume (hyperuricemia)
</anorexia-nervosa>

<disease-prevention>
primary - preventing the disease
secondary - early detection
teriary - limit disease progression
</disease-prevention>

<retroperitoneal-bleeding>
Discoloration around the umbilicus (Cullen's sign) or flank (Grey Turner's sign)
Abdominal pain or numbness of lower extremities (due to spinal nerve compression
Volume replacement is the priority using colloid or crystalloid solutions
</retroperitoneal-bleeding>

<vasopressin>
Should replace fluid first before adminstration of vasopressin
</vasopressin>

<tension-pneumothorax>
Tracheal deviation
Hypotension
</tension-pneumothorax>


<neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>
Complication resulting from antipsychotic medications
Could occur even with one dose of me\dissatisfaction, therefore must always monitor temperature when administering antipsychotics
</neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>

<escherichia-coli>
Does not need contact precautions unless the client is incontinent or is wearing a diaper. 
</escherichia-coli>

<glomerulonephritis>
Causes an elevated serum anti-streptolysin o (ASO) titer
</glomerulonephritis>

<psoriasis>
Presents as white, silvery, scaly patches on the skin 
Most common areas are elbows, knees, scalp and scrotum
</psoriasis>


<radiation-safety>
Visitation no more than 30min
Distance no less than 6 feet
No pregnant staff or visitors
</radiation-safety>

<myelomeningocele>
Cover with moist dressing
Take great care to avoid rupture, as CNS infection would be imminent 
Surgery done 24-48 hours after birth   
</myelomeningocele>

</review>