<review>

<coagulation>
Prothrombin Time - monitors <blr>extrnisic</blr> pathway and <blr>warfarin</blr> therapy - normal values are <blr>11-12</blr> seconds. Theraputic values are <blr>22-36</blr> seconds.
INR = (measured PT) / (reference PT)
Partial thromboplastin time - monitors <blr>intrinsic</blr> pathway - normal range is <blr>25-35</blr> seconds. Theraputic values of <blr>60-100</blr> seconds (1.5 - 2.5x)
</coagulation>

<phlebitis>
<blr>Discontinue</blr> infusion and apply a <blr>warm soak</blr>, document
<blr>No need to</blr> contact the prescriber
</phlebitis>

<transfusion>
Blood should be transfused within <blr>2-4</blr> hours
Needle guage should be <blr>18-20G</blr> to insure that cells aren't damaged
Monitor clients for first <blr>15</blr> min then <blr>periodically</blr> after 
</transfusion>

<urine>
Normal out put is <blr>800 to 2000</blr> mL/day (<blr>30-80</blr> ml/hour)
</urine>

<benzodiazepines>
Don't <blr>ambulate</blr> clients after administering a benzo, even to the <blr>bathroom</blr>
Don't administer <blr>an opiod</blr> after a benzo, due to risk of <blr>respiratory depression</blr>
</benzodiazepines>


<preoperative>
teaching about the <blr>procedure</blr> and <blr>experience</blr>, taching about <blr>pain</blr> and <blr>pain relief</blr>, controling client's <blr>anxiety</blr>, basic needs like <blr>elimination</blr> are met, maintain <blr>NPO status</blr>
Alert the <blr>anesthesiologist</blr> of any <blr>PO meds</blr> given prior 
</preoperative>

<multiple-sclerosis>
treatment is with <blr>beta interferon</blr>
</multiple-sclerosis>

<parkinson>
Early symptoms: <blr>fatigue</blr>, <blr>loss of smell</blr>
</parkinson>

<dialysis>
Administering an <blr>antihypertensive</blr> prior to could lead to <blr>hypotension</blr>, the nurse should wait until after dialysis to administer it.
<blr>Antimicrobials</blr> and <blr>antibiotics</blr> are removed with the dialysate solution, should be withheld until after. 
</dialysis>

<influenza>
FDA approved antivirals: <blr>peramivir</blr>, <blr>zanamivir</blr>, <blr>oseltamivir</blr>, <blr>baloxavir</blr>
Antivirals <blr>decrease the efficacy</blr> of the vaccine
</influenza>

<glasgow-coma-scale>
Assesses three areas of conciousness - <blr>verbal response</blr>, <blr>motor response</blr>, <blr>eye opening</blr>
Maximum score is <blr>15</blr>, minimal score is <blr>3</blr>
Eyes open (1-4): <blr>none</blr>, <blr>to pain</blr>, <blr>to speech</blr>, <blr>spontaneously</blr>
Verbal (1-5): <blr>none</blr>, <blr>incomprehensible</blr>, <blr>inappropriate</blr>, <blr>confused</blr>, <blr>oriented</blr>
Motor (1-6): <blr>none</blr>, <blr>abnormal extension</blr>, <blr>abnormal flexion</blr>, <blr>withdrawl</blr>, <blr>localizes pain</blr>, <blr>obeys commands</blr>
</glasgow-coma-scale>

<ascites>
Abdominal skin is <blr>taut</blr> and <blr>glistening</blr>
</ascites>

<bladder-distension>
<blr>Dull percussion</blr> over symphisis pubis
</bladder-distension>

<sickle-cell-crisis>
<blr>Fluids</blr> are used to reduce blood viscosity
<blr>Activity</blr> is limited to reduce <blr>oxygen needs</blr>
Diet is used to promote <blr>metabolic demand</blr>, rich in <blr>calories</blr> and high in <blr>protein</blr>
<blr>Oxygen</blr> is atministed to prevent further cell sickling
Pain management should be done with a combination of <blr>opiod</blr> and <blr>nonopiod</blr> drugs, not just <blr>nonopioid</blr>, as pain could be severe
</sickle-cell-crisis>

<low-molecular-weight-heparin>
<blr>aPTT</blr> is not used to monitor them, <blr>no frequent</blr> blood tests are required
Given to prevent <blr>lower limb blood clots</blr>
Lower risk of bleeding than <blr>heparin</blr>, but the risk is still present
</low-molecular-weight-heparin>

<LPN-duties>
All clients must be <blr>stable</blr> and require <blr>ruoutine</blr>, <blr>unchaning</blr> procedures, they cannot care for clients who require <blr>assessments</blr> 
<blr>Colostomy</blr> care
Administering <blr>oral</blr> meds
</LPN-duties>

<potassium>
Low - flattened <blr>T waves</blr>, prominent <blr>U waves</blr>, <blr>ST-</blr>segment <blr>depression</blr>, prolonged <blr>PR interval</blr>, 
</potassium>

<para-thyroid-hormone>
Primary target is the <blr>kidney</blr> and <blr>bone</blr>
Causes blood levels of calcium to <blr>rise</blr> 
Causes <blr>calcium</blr> conservation in the kidney
</para-thyroid-hormone>

<calcium>
Bound with <blr>fatty acids</blr>
</calcium>

<nsaid>
Increase <blr>blood pressure</blr>, counterindicated in individuals with <blr>hypertension</blr>
Affect <blr>platelet clotting</blr>, increase the risk of <blr>bleeding</blr> especially with 
</nsaid>

<cholelithiasis>
Risk factors include <blr>Native American</blr> and <blr>Hispanic</blr> origins, <blr>obesity</blr>, <blr>multiparousness</blr>, age over <blr>40</blr>, <blr>fasting</blr>
</cholelithiasis>

<alcohol-withdrawal>
Signs and symptoms: elevated <blr>temperature</blr>, nocturnal <blr>leg cramps</blr>, generalized <blr>muscle pain</blr> and <blr>malaise</blr>, <blr>tremors</blr>
</alcohol-withdrawal>

<ibuprofen>
Maximum daliy dosage: <blr>3,200</blr> mg/day
</ibuprofen>

<statin>
Must be given at night when <blr>cholesterol</blr> production is highest
</statin>

<hemolytic-transfusion-reaction>
Symptoms: <blr>chills</blr>, <blr>low back/chest</blr> pain, <blr>hypotension</blr>, <blr>tachycardia</blr>
Treatment: stop the <blr>transfusion</blr>, obtain a <blr>urine specime</blr>, maintain <blr>blood volume</blr> and <blr>renal perfusion</blr> with an <blr>IV colloid solution</blr> (like <blr>albumin</blr>, <blr>gelatin</blr>, <blr>dextran</blr>, <blr>starch</blr>).
</hemolytic-transfusion-reaction>

<febrile-transfusion-reaction>
Temperature increase > <blr>1 degree Celsius</blr>
<blr>Headache</blr>, <blr>Nausea</blr>, <blr>vomiting</blr>
</febrile-transfusion-reaction>

<who-do-you-see-first-rules>
Is the client stable or unstable? Eliminate stable clients.
Is the client experiencing expected or unexpeced findings? Eliminate expecting findgins. 
Are the reminaing answers referring to airway, breathing or circulation (ABCs)? Eliminate each non-priority answer option using the ABCs.
Are the reminaing asnwer options real (actual) or potential problems? Eliminate the potential problem answer options.
</who-do-you-see-first-rules>

<systemic-lupus-erythematosus>
Malar rash - rash extending across the nasal bridge and upper cheeks.
</systemic-lupus-erythematosus>

<chronic-kidney-disease>
Foods to avoid: citrus fruit, they are high in potassium as damaged kidneys cannot remove it. 
Dried fruits, avocado, tomato, potatoes and bananas. 
Calcium is lost through the damaged kidneys.
Dairy products are high in phosphorus which binds even more calcium and should be avoided.
Dietary protein incrases uric acid (urea) production which cannot be cleared by the damaged kidneys. Dietary protein should be kept at low or normal levels (but not incrased).
</chronic-kidney-disease>

<right-sided-heart-failure>
Congestion of the gastric veins, resulting in anorexia and eventual development of ascites
</right-sided-heart-failure>

<lithium-toxicity>
Early signs: nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, tremors and twitching. 
Late signs: fever, ataxia, confusion, and seizures.
</lithium-toxicity>

<fluid-intake>
Normal fluid intake should be between 1,500 - 2,000 ml/day
</fluid-intake>

<skin-grafting>
Priority should be given to grafit immobilization, since the graft must adhere to the site for vascularization to take place. It takes between 7-10 days to adhere. 
</skin-grafting>

<low-hemoglobin>
First apply oxygen to make sure the available hemoglobin is well oxygenated, place on cariac monitor, start the intravenous catheter, draw the blood work.
</low-hemoglobin>

<hyperkalemia>
Elevated T-waves
</hyperkalemia>

<cushing-disease>
Overproduction of corticosteroids, mainly cortisol or hypercortisolism. 
Cortisol is associated with an incrase in glucose levels, increased sodium levels, decreased potassium and calcium levels. 
</cushing-disease>

<corticosteroid>
Increases levels of glucose, increases sodium levels, decreases potassium and calcium levels
</corticosteroid>


<liver-failure>
Underproduction of bicarbonate leads to metabolic-acidosis 
</liver-failure>

<ascites>
Pushes on the lungs, decreasing lung capacity
</ascites>

<acidosis>
Associated with hyperkalemia
</acidosis>

<hyperkalemia> 
Treatment is to administer insulin, insulin activates sodium-proton pump which pumps sodium ions in to the cell and hydrogen ions out, the influx of sodium activates the the sodium-potassium pump which job it's to maintain intracellular potassium concentrations higher and sodium concentrations lower. The Na-K pump exports 3 ions of sodium and imports two ions of potassium, lowering the overall serum potassium concentration.
Symptom is an elevated T wave
</hyperkalemia> 

<fetal-kick-counting>
Must be done the same time each day, preferrably after a meal in the left side lying position.
Should not be less then 10 kicks in 2 hours, or less then 3 kickins in one hour.
If the test fails, then a non-stress test should be performed. 
</fetal-kick-counting>

<above-knee-amputation>
Compression dressing should be maintained to minimize edema, prevent infection and shape the stubb. 
Elevate the amputated limb for 24 hours after surgery. 
Range of motion excercises every 2-4 hours.
No sitting in chair for prolonged times to prevent hip flexion contractions.
</above-knee-amputation>

<milieu-therapy>
Intended to treat behaviour and personality disorders. All aspects of the environemnt are utilized to alter the behaviour and personality. Each member is assigned a set of responsibilities and activities that allow them to develop healthy social behaviours. 
Keys to successful therapy: support, structure, repetition, consistent expectations.
</milieu-therapy>

<alzheimer>
Reduced anxiety first then reorient the client. 
Reduce anxiety by staying with the client and explaining the environment. 
Clients may be calmer in the morning and get more agitated as the day progresses. 
</alzheimer>

<hepatitis-a>
Spread via fecal-oral route.
In pediatric clients symptoms are flu like in nature, including anorexia, fever, malaise, lethargy, clay colored stools, dark urine. Jaundice is not common in pediatric patients. 
Before age 6, 70% of patients will be asymptomatic. 
</hepatitis-a>

<myxedema>
Refers to severe hypothyroidisim.
Symptoms: very cold, tired and sluggish.
</myxedema>

<poisoning>
Call Poison Control Center not 911
</poisoning>

<uterine-hyper-tonicity>
When one contractions lasts 2 minutes or longer or when there are 5 or more contractions in 10 minutes.
</uterine-hyper-tonicity>


<infant-respiratory-rate>
Less then 66 breaths per minute (normal), if greater then tachypnea
</infant-respiratory-rate>

<toilet-training>
Ready between 18 months to 3 years
Parents must have 2 weeks of free time off work.
Child must be able to sit for 5-10 minutes.
Must be able to have fine motor skills to dress and unrdress.
</toilet-training>

<pediatric-cardiac-defect>
Check child for hypoxia which is indicated by squatting after activity, cyanosis, tachycardia and sweating.
</pediatric-cardiac-defect>

<chronic-alcohol-abuse>
Hypomagnesemia - trermors, confusion, racing heart - could be dangerous is severe. 
</chronic-alcohol-abuse>

<urinary-incontinence>
Toilet schedule - voiding every 2 hours
Stress incontinence - occurs when abdominal pressure increases due to sneezing, laughter etc. 
Urge incontinence - occurs after experience sudden urge to void, with an inability to suppress urination before reaching bathroom. 
</urinary-incontinence>

<hypocalcemia>
tetany - spasms of hands, legs and feet, could also result in breating and cardio disturbances, overactive deep tendon reflexes, muscle twitching.
Chvostek sign - facial contraction when tapping on the facial nerve.
Trousseau sign - muscle scpasm of the hand and wrist when blood pressure cuff is applied.
Finger numbness.
</hypocalcemia>

<deep-vein-thrombosis>
Do not massage, promote bed rest and not moving the extremity, elevate the extremity on pillows to reduce edema and promote venous return. 
</deep-vein-thrombosis>

<tuberculosis> 
Transporting - a patient with TB should be wearing a surgical mask (not N95) and the persons caring for them should be alerted and wear N95.
</tuberculosis>

<sickle-cell-crisis>
Blood test shows increased reticulocyte (immature red blood cells) count.
Hematocrit is decreased. 
Hemoglobin level is decreased. 
Causes: hypoxemia, dehydration, infection, excessive esercise, cold temperatures.
Treatment: oxygenation, hydration, adequate rest, warmth. 
</sickle-cell-crisis>

<IV-Push>
Port nearest to the insertion site.
Tubing above should be clamped.
Use a watch with to time push duration
</IV-Push>

<scabies>
Transmission of scabies occurs through mites. 
</scabies>

<escherichia-coli>
Transmitted by fecal-oral route, causes acute diarrhea.
Standard precautions are enough unless the client is incontinetn or is diapered, then contact precautions are needed. 
</escherichia-coli>

<hepatitis-a>
Transmitted through a fecal-oral route.
Standard precautiuons are enough unless incontinent or diapered, then contact precautions are needed. 
</hepatitis-a>

<gastrostomy-tube>
Monitor prealbumin levels, it has shorter half life than albumin and is a better reflection of the patient's nutritional status.
</gastrostomy-tube>

<poly-cystic-ovarian-syndrome>
Metabolic disorder diagnosed in adolescence. Characterized by ovulatory dysfunction, amenorrhea, cysts in the ovaries, hyperandrogenism.
Most common in women under 30 and may cause infertility. 
Hormonal changes include increased testosterone, decreased progesterone and increased insulin resistance. 
Causes moood instability, stubborn weight gain, hair growth on face (hirsutism), acne. 
Women must strive to maintain normal weight, which can result in a more regular menstrual cycle. 
</poly-cystic-ovarian-syndrome>

<leadership-models>
Transformational leader - communicate their vision in a manner that is meaningful and exciting, insipires commitment from others and encourages self-motivation
Autocratic leader - (ruler with absolute power) leader makes decision with no input from staff.
Laissez faire leader - (french for let it be) leader does not want to make decisions but lets other decide.
Democratic leader - leader seeks inputs from staff before making decisions, primarly concernec with human relations and teamwork.
</leadership-models>

<neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>
Life threatening idiosynchratic reaction to dopamine receptor-antagonist drugs.
Usually occurs 4-14 days after the start of therapy. 
Symptoms: sudden high fever, rigidity, tachycardia, hypertension, decreased level of consciousness. 
Bromocriptine should be administered, it counteracts the effects of dopamine antagonists. 
</neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>

<bromocriptine>
Dopamine receptor agonist.
Reduces prolacting levels (treats hyperprolactinemia).
Treats acromegaly by decreasing the amounts of human growth hormone.
Treats Parkinson's disease. 
</bromocriptine>

<sequential-compression-devices>
Remove at least once every 8 hours.
Monitor for one full cycle after applying.
</sequential-compression-devices>

<iron-supplements>
Should be taken on empty stomach, with vitamin C enriched juice.
</iron-supplements>

<sulfonyureas>
Developed in 1950's.
Increase the release of insulin from the pancreas.
Common meds in class:
glyburide, glimepiride, glipizide
Common interactions: beta blockers - mask hypoglycemia which is the primary adverse effect of oral antidiabetic agents.
Gemfibrozil - cholesterol medication, could increase the hypoglycemic effects of sulfonyureas.
Aspirin and oral anticoagulants, MAOIs, sulfonamides (antibiotics mostly for UTI), cimetidine  - displace the sulfonyureas from the transport proteins, thereby increasing their effect
Thiazides, Isoniazid, Phenytoin, Corticosteroids - decrease the effects of sulfonyureas.
</sulfonyureas>

<ginkgo-biloba>
Can cause bleeding, taking it with other meds that cause bleeding can increase the effect. 
Thought to increase mental fitness. Studies failed to show any increase except in dimentia. 
</ginkgo-biloba>

<ginseng>
Increases the hypoglycemic effects of sulfonyureas.
Boost energy, lowers blood sugar and cholesterol, reduces stress, manages sexual dysfunction.
</ginseng>


<ibuprofen>
Increases the hypoglycemic effect of oral antidiabetics.
Increases risk of bleeding.
Increases risk of heart attack and stroke as early as a week after taking it consistently.
</ibuprofen>

<lumbar-puncture>
Food and fluids are not restricted
After procedure instruct the client to lay flat for 6-8 hours
Encourage fluids 
</lumbar-puncture>

<cancer>
Most common cancer deaths are from smoking associated lung cancer. 
Most common cancer diagnosis is from skin cancer.
</cancer>

<live-vaccines>
Measles, mumps, rubella (MMR), varicella (chicken pox), small pox, rotavirus, influenza.
Should not be given to pregnant women, vaccinate in postpartum period, because of the theoretical risk of tranmission to the fetus. 
Influenza vaccines are recommended if pregnant during the influenza season. 
Inactivated vaccines such as influenza, tetanus, hep B could be given.
</live-vaccines>

<low-back-pain>
Don't straing to reach for things.
Do not lie in prone position.
Avoid knee and hip extension.
</low-back-pain>

<meningitis>
Fever, neck pain and stiffness, Headache
</meningitis>

<basal-skull-fracture>
CNS leak from the ear
</basal-skull-fracture>

<suicide>
Ask about frequency, duration and intensity of suicidal thoughts (suicidal ideation).
Ask abou the suicide plan like the method and time and place.
Ask about prior attempts or rehersals. 
Evaluate the intent to follow through with the plan. 
Maintain a safe environment and place on constant observation. 
</suicide>

<influenza-vaccine> 
Fever is common and expected side effect, up to 39C (102.8F)
</influenza-vaccine>

<shock>
Hypovolemic, cardiogenic, obstructive, distributive (neurogenic, septic, anaphylectic).
Signs and symptoms: tachycardia, low blood pressure, palor. 
</shock>

<hyperthyroidism>
Tachycardia, intolerance to heat, polyphagia (excessive eating), nervousness and dry hair as well as hypertension. 
</hyperthyroidism>

<vena-cava-syndrome>
Aka: supine hypotensive syndrome
Reduction of cardiac output when the gravid uterus puts pressure on the vena cava, especially in the supine position.
Lying on the side, takes the pressure off the vena cava.
</vena-cava-syndrome>

<retinal-detachment>
Medical emergency.
Feels like a curtain is being pulled over eyes.
</retinal-detachment>

<meningitis>
Monitor for deterioration: decreased LOC, Cushing triad, impaired pupil reactivity to light.
</meningitis>

<cushing-triad>
Indicates increase in intracranial pressure. 
Bradycardia, irregular respirations, widened pulse pressure. 
</cushing-triad>

<play-by-age>
Infant (0-1) - solitary play, focusted on their own activity but enjoy the presence of others.
Toddler (1-3) - parallel play, playing along side but not with others.  
</play-by-age>

<mastitis>
Blocked duct due to bacterial infection, causes reddned inflamed painful breast. 
Treated with antibiotics. 
Cracked nipples.
Risk factor is poor hygine.
Failure to empty while breastfeeding. 
</mastitis>


<tricuspid-valve>
Auscultate at S1: 5th intercostal, left sternal border. 
</tricuspid-valve>

<nebulizer>
Delivers medication through water mist. 
Excessive use can cause hypervolemia due to excessive fluid absorption. 
</nebulizer>

<restraints>
Room where easily seen.
Food and water every 2 hours.
Monitor skin integrity every 30 mintues to monitor for redness. 
Toilet every 2 hours.
Range of motion for 10 min every 2 hours. 
Monitor every 15 min then every hour. 
</restraints>

<methycillin-resistant-staphylococcus-aureus>
Contact precautions.
</methycillin-resistant-staphylococcus-aureus>

<neisseria-meningitidis> 
Droplet precautions.
</neisseria-meningitidis>

<mycobacterium-tuberculosis>
Airborne precautions. 
</mycobacterium-tuberculosis>

<mean-arterial-pressure>
Should be at least 65.
MAP = (S+2D)/3; where S is the systolic pressure and D is the diastollic pressure. 
</mean-arterial-pressure>

<hypotension>
Begin fluid resuscitation with crystalloid solution of at least 30ml/kg over 30 min. 
If fluids don't work begin norepinephrine (Levophed) or dopamine.
</hypotension>

<hypothermia>
Shivering increases oxygen consumption. 
</hypothermia>

<hyperthermia> 
Give acetaminophen and apply a cooling blanket. 
</hyperthermia> 

<extravasation>
Happen when caustic IV solution leaks outside of the blood vessel and irritates the tissue. 
Symptoms include pain, burning and edema around the IV site.
</extravasation>

<infiltration>
Happens when non caustic IV solution leaks outside of the blood vessel. 
</infiltration>

<skin-patch>
Heat greatly increases medicine absoprtion and could result in an overdose. 
</skin-patch>

<aminophylline>
Interacts with propranolol, decreasing the bodies ability to metaboloize it leading to toxicity.
</aminophylline>

<monoamine-oxidase-inhibitors>
Avoid tyramine
Common medications in this class: isocarboxazid. 
</monoamine-oxidase-inhibitors>

<renal-calculi>
To prevent, ingest between 2,500 - 3,000 mL of fluid per day. 
</renal-calculi>

<magnetic-resonsnace-imaging>
Presence of anyurism clips is contraindicated as they could be made from a ferromagnetic material. 
</magnetic-resonsnace-imaging>

<brachytherapy>
Surgical placement of irradiated beads near the tumor. 
All treatments should be clustered together as to not come into the patient's room too many times. 
Pregnant women and children should avoid contact with the patient.
Other visitors are allowed after 24 post insertion, visits must be limited to 30 min.
</brachytherapy>

<walker>
Lift the walker, don't slide it, 8-10 inches ahead.
</walker>

<alcohol-withdrawal>
Symptoms occur 4-6 hours after last drink and last up to 14 days.
Treatment is to use benzodiazepines to alleviate the agitation. 
Common benzodiazapeine to use is chlordiazepoxide. 
Symtpoms - tremor, insomnia, dilated pupils, tachycardia, perspiration, hallucinations.
</alcohol-withdrawal>

<cardiac-temponade>

</cardiac-temponade>



<hypocalcemia>
Muscle cramps, Chvostek sign (facial nerve spasm), Trousseaue's sign (bp cuff dorsiflexion)
</hypocalcemia>

<hypercalcemia>
Weakness, nausea, polyurea  
</hypercalcemia>

<restraints>
Before applying restraints check for co-occuring medical conditions that may contraindicate their use such as vomiting or seizures. 
</restraints>

<trigeminal-nerve>
Sensation of touch on face
Controlling muscles needed to chew
</trigeminal-nerve>

<Alzheimers>
Restlessness and pacing
</Alzheimers>

<cessarian-section>
Legs could be numb from local anesthetic, which is a normal finding.
</cessarian-section>

<myasthenia-gravis>
Corticosteroids are often a part of the treatment schedule.
</myasthenia-gravis>

<incident-report>
Should be completed when the staff or clients are subject to danger, such as wrong medication, complications from procedures like extravasation, breask in asceptic technique, client refuses treatment, client voices dissatisfaction with care that cannot be resolved. 
Does not go into the client record, used for management purposes. 
</incident-report>

<chronic-kidney-disease>
Diet includes increased calories, animal protein (not plant), low potassium, low phosphorus and low sodium, limit dairy to 1 cup of milk or 1 ounce of cheese per day (because of phosphorus limits)
</chronic-kidney-disease>

<potassium-rich-foods>
Beets, oranges, melons, tomatoes, dried beans, cooked greens, brown rice, dairy, whole wheat bread
</potassium-rich-foods>

<chronic-kidney-disease>
Limit potassium and phosphorus. 
</chronic-kidney-disease>

<phosphorus-rich-foods>
Dairy products (except brie cheese, sherbet, cream cheese, ricotta cheese)
Whole wheat cereals, oatmeal, bran and granola 
</phosphorus-rich-foods>

<suicide-assessment>
Intent to Die - how serious a patient is in carrying through
Severity of ideation - how persistent are the thoughts
Degree of planning 
</suicide-assessment>

<lithium>
Expected side effects - fine hand tremor, polyuria and polydypsia. 
Maintaince dose is reached after 7-14 days.
</lithium>

<cephalohematoma>
Does not cross suture lines
</cephalohematoma>

<systemic-inflammatory-response-syndrome>
Caused by mechanical tissue trauma and tissue ischemia, could lead to multi organ Failure
Release of inflammatory markers, activation of coagulation cascade, decreased perfusion and hypotension
</systemic-inflammatory-response-syndrome>

<anorexia-nervosa>
Refusal to eat for the fear of gaining weight
Increased BUN due to lower blood volume (hyperuricemia)
</anorexia-nervosa>

<disease-prevention>
primary - preventing the disease
secondary - early detection
teriary - limit disease progression
</disease-prevention>

<retroperitoneal-bleeding>
Discoloration around the umbilicus (Cullen's sign) or flank (Grey Turner's sign)
Abdominal pain or numbness of lower extremities (due to spinal nerve compression
Volume replacement is the priority using colloid or crystalloid solutions
</retroperitoneal-bleeding>

<vasopressin>
Should replace fluid first before adminstration of vasopressin
</vasopressin>

<tension-pneumothorax>
Tracheal deviation
Hypotension
</tension-pneumothorax>


<neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>
Complication resulting from antipsychotic medications
Could occur even with one dose of me\dissatisfaction, therefore must always monitor temperature when administering antipsychotics
</neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>

<escherichia-coli>
Does not need contact precautions unless the client is incontinent or is wearing a diaper. 
</escherichia-coli>

<glomerulonephritis>
Causes an elevated serum anti-streptolysin o (ASO) titer
</glomerulonephritis>

<psoriasis>
Presents as white, silvery, scaly patches on the skin 
Most common areas are elbows, knees, scalp and scrotum
</psoriasis>


<radiation-safety>
Visitation no more than 30min
Distance no less than 6 feet
No pregnant staff or visitors
</radiation-safety>

<myelomeningocele>
Cover with moist dressing
Take great care to avoid rupture, as CNS infection would be imminent 
Surgery done 24-48 hours after birth   
</myelomeningocele>


<gun-safety>
Store ammunition separately from guns
Guns should never be stored loaded
</gun-safety>

<deep-tendon-reflexes>
Rated on a 4 point scale 
0 - no response
1 - slight, but definitive response
2 - brisk; normal
3 - very brisk
4 - overactive - abnormal
</deep-tendon-reflexes>

<respiratory-rate>
Normal is 12 and higher per minute
</respiratory-rate>

<magnesium>
Acts as a smooth muscle relaxer, resulsts in vasodialtion and reduced blood pressure
Normal levels 1.3 - 2.1 mEq/L
</magnesium>

<Addisons-disease>
Hyposecrion of adrenal hormones
Causes hyponatremia, hypotension, fatigue and muscle cramps
Hyperkalemia due to decreased potassium release
Could result in hypercalcemia
Tanned skin without sun exposure
Hairloss due to reduced androgen levels, especially in females because adrenals produce most androgens in females
Hypoglycemia due to reduction of cortisol
Gastric acid production decreases
</Addisons-disease>

<Hyperkalemia>
Promotes reabsorption of hydrogen ions, leading to acidosis. 
</Hyperkalemia>

<aldosterone>
Main mineralcorticoid produced by the zona glomerulosa of the adrenal gland
Essential for sodium conservation
</aldosterone>

<epipen>
Inject into the vastus lateralis muscle
</epipen>

<oral-contraceptives>
Suppress the production of breastmilk, if the client is breastfeeind other methods of contraception should be used.
</oral-contraceptives>

<intra-ocular-pressure>
Normal is 21 or below
</intra-ocular-pressure>

<glaucoma>
If the pressure readings are borderline, pressure should be take at multiple points throughout the day.
Secondary glaucoma could be caused by neurovasuclar disorders, such as CVAs.
Vision loss occurs in peripheral vision initially.
Open-Angle - affects both eyes simultaneously, slow progression
Closed-Angle - usually affects one eye at a time. 
More common in black race - six fold incrase
Other risk factors include being higly far sighted.
</glaucoma>

<colorectal-cancer>
Risk factors - African American, BMI > 30, smoking, alcohol consumption > 4 drinks per week, red meat > 7 servings per week, relatives with the disease 
When considering who is at higher risk, count the risk factors
</colorectal-cancer>

<fall>
Complete a physical assessment of the client to make sure they didn't sustain any injuries, if they didn't: fill out an incident report then call the provider, then call the family.
</fall>

<T4>
Normal T4 levels are 5.0 - 12.0 microgram/dL 
</T4>

<lithium>
Could decrease thyroid hormone(T4) secretion.
</lithium> 

<leukocytes>
Normal levels are between 4.5 -11k units per microliter.
</leukocytes>

<hyponatremia>
Body compensates for low sodium by retaining lithium. 
</hyponatremia>

<dementia>
Common to self isolate while eating.
</dementia>

<tuberculin-skin-test>
Administration of a live-virus-vaccine may cause a false negative on a TST.
If administering a live virus vaccine it should be done on the same day as the TST or waiting 4-6 weeks after a live vaccine. 
False negative could also occur due to a weakened immune system.
Bacille Calmette-Guerin (vaccine) could give a false positive if given within 4-6 weeks of TST.
</tuberculin-skin-test>

<corticosteroid>
Suppress the immune system and could give a false negative on tuberculin-skin-test.
</corticosteroid>

<acquired-immondeficinecy-syndrome>
Could produce a false negative on a tuberculin-skin-test due to immune system supresssion.
</acquired-immondeficinecy-syndrome>


<tuberculosis>
A diagnosis is confirmed when a sputum sample is cultured.
</tuberculosis>

<live-virus-vaccine>
Vaccines for herpes zoster (shingles), measles vaccine and mumps vaccine.   
</live-virus-vaccine>

<peripherally-inserted-central-catheter>
In case the catheter breaks, tourniquet the arm by the shoulder - then check to make sure the arm still has a radial pulse (don't want to complete occlude the blood flow), then order an x-ray.
Do not move the client to prevent movement of the catheter piece.
</peripherally-inserted-central-catheter>

<dysphagia>
Level 1 - pureed foods, need no chewing.
Level 2 - mechanically altered foods, moist foods that needs some chewing. Examples are meatloaf with mash and gravy. Meats should be ground and gavies are used to soften. 
Level 3 - advanced diet, soft solid foods need more chewing. Example would be pasta, thinly sliced chicken. Exclude foods that are tough, cruncy or sticky.
Level 4 - general diet, all foods included.
</dysphagia>

<hypernatremia>
Could be caused by diabetes-insipidus 
</hypernatremia>

<diabetes-insipidus>
Characterized by a decrease in anti-diuretic-hormone.
Causes increased urine output and increased sodium concentrations.
Excretion of dilute urine at 200 ml/hr +
</diabetes-insipidus>

<urine-specific-gravity>
Normal range is 1.010 - 1.030
</urine-specific-gravity>

<access-port>
Should be scrubbed for 30-60 seconds prior to use.
</access-port>

<abuse>
Risk factors for older adults: female, reduced social interaction, at least one physical or mental impairment. 
</abuse>

<fetal-heart-rate>
Should be heard with a doppler at 10-12 weeks.
</fetal-heart-rate>

<ballotment>
Movement of the fetus that is palpated with a tap on the uterus.
Should be first felt at 4-5 months.
</ballotment>

<aminoglycosides>
Example: gentamycin
Side effects: ototoxicity, nephgrotoxicity.
</aminoglycosides>

<gentamycin>
An aminoglycoside antibiotics.
Treats infections caused by pseudomonas aeruginosa, Escherichia-coli and staphylococcus. 
</gentamycin>

<dipstick-urinalisys>
Tests for: specific gravity, pH, protein, leukocytes, blood, ketones, glucose
</dipstick-urinalisys>

<straight-catherterization>
In home setting: no need for sterile procedures, catheters are reused after washing them with anti-bacterial soap and povidone-iodine.
</straight-catherterization>

<right-hemisphere>
Responsible for identifying person, place and times.
Responsible for controlling impulsive behaviour.
</right-hemisphere>

<left-hemisphere>
Controls speech, math skills and analytical thinking. 
</left-hemisphere>

<chronic-kidney-disease>
Diet needs to be low in protein, sodium, potassium and phosphorus. 
</chronic-kidney-disease>

<hypoglycemia>
Blood glucose less than 60mg/dL
Treatments when concious - 15-20g of rapid acting sugars such as 4oz fruit juice or soda, 8 oz milk, tablespoon of sugar
Treatments when semiconcious - 1mg glucagon IM or SC or 25-50 mg 50% dextrose IV.
</hypoglycemia>

<macular-degeneration>
After surgery the client has to remain face down. 
</macular-degeneration>

<cataract>
After surgery: avoid activitives that increase IOP such as bending or lifting heavy equipment (more than 10-15lbs) 
</cataract>

<liver-failure>
Decrease fat in diet, incrase calories, increase carbs, decrease sodium, decrease fluids to manage ascites. Protein should be lowered if ammonia is high or should be raised if it's not.
</liver-failure>

<Jackson-Pratt-drain>
To remove: release the suction, remove sutures, ask patient to breath deeply and regularly, pull drain out in one motion, assess the exit site and cover it with gauze. 
</Jackson-Pratt-drain>

<sterile-field>
Keep hands at or above table level
1in edge of the sterile field is non sterile and could only be touched with clean golve (not sterile glove)
</sterile-field>

<peripherally-inserted-central-catheter>
Clean around the catheter in circular motion and away.
Dressing changes require sterile technique
Old dressing should be removed toward the insertion site.
Change gloves after removing the old dressing.
</peripherally-inserted-central-catheter>

<continuous-renal-replacement-therapy>
Indications: patients who have cardiovascular impartments that can't tolerate low BP that accompanies hemodialysis.
Slow continuous filtering of the blood.
Does not require a av fistula, blood is drawn from femoral or subcalvian vein. 
Hemofilter should be changed every 24-48 hours
Clients are prone to hypothermia
</continuous-renal-replacement-therapy>

<isoniazid>
Could induce hepatitis/liver-failure.
</isoniazid>

<hepatitis>
Early symptoms are nausea and anorexia.
</hepatitis>

<Jaundice>
Best places to assesss for jaundice are abdomen skin, sclera of the eyes and hard pallete.
In Asian-American populations, skin may have a natural yellow tone so the best place to assess for jaundice in this populace is the hard pallete. 
</Jaundice>

<tuberculosis>
Medications used: isoniazid, rifampin, pyrazinamide, ethambutol
</tuberculosis>

<LPN-delegation>
Stable clients.
Cannot delegate teaching or tasks that require assessment. 
</LPN-delegation>

<syndrome-of-inappropriate-antidiuretic-hormone-secretion>
Causes the body to retain too much water.
Dilutional hyponatremia occurs.
Hypervolemia causes tachycardia.
Treatment includes restricting fluid intake to 500-600ml/24h, diuretics, daily weights and strict intake and output.
End result is seizures and brain swelling. 
</syndrome-of-inappropriate-antidiuretic-hormone-secretion>

<Hypervolemia>
Causes tachycardia.
</Hypervolemia>

<newborn-facial-paralysis>
Occurs because of compression of cranial nerve VII, usually resolves in a few days to 3 weeks, or could be permanent. 
</newborn-facial-paralysis>

<neonatal-red-reflex>
Should be present in both eyes and should be symmetrical. 
If not present or not symmetrical it is considered an opthalmic emergency.
Absense could cause blindness if not treated right away.
</neonatal-red-reflex>

<sterile-field>
Situations where sterile field is required: dialysis catheters, chest tube insertion, inserting central venous or arterial lines, inserting drainage devices.
</sterile-field>

<iliostomy>
If constipated then massage around the stoma prmoting peristalsis, drink warm fluids they promote peristalsis and provide a mild cathartic effect, take a warm shower which helps promote abdominal muscle relaxation
</iliostomy>

<constipation>
Drink warm fluids they promote peristalsis and provide a mild cathartic effect, take a warm shower which helps promote abdominal muscle relaxation
</constipation> 

<dehydration>
Drink a solution high in sodium and potassium.
</dehydration>

<cyanosis>
In dark skinned clinets assesed on light skin areas such as the soles of feet and palms of hands, oral cavity membranes and conjunctiva with bluish or light gray color.
</cyanosis>

<post-traumatic-stress-disorder>
Tendancy for violence and suicide. 
Allow talk of traumatic event.
Teach about conditioning.
Remove weapons from space.
</post-traumatic-stress-disorder>

<diphenhydramine>
Has anticholinergic properties.
Contraindicated in closed angle glaucoma, small bowel obstruction - may increase obstruction, and peptic ulcers as it may increase bleeding.
</diphenhydramine>

<status-epilepticus>
Tonic-clonic (tonic - extension of arms/legs, clonic - contraction of arms and legs) should not last more than 60-90 seconds. Seizure followed by small rest then followed by another sezure or a seizure that lasts more than 5 minutes
is called status epilepticus. 
Benzodiazapeines like diazapam are presricbed as they increase the seizure threshold in the brain. Given IV push, rectally or nasaly. 
</status-epilepticus>

<seizure>
Lay on side so saliva can drain. Give oxygen if there are color changes. Lower clinet to floor, protect the head, clear objects from area. Administer Lore/diazepam. Stay with the client until alert. 
</seizure>

<Hodgekin-lymphoma>
Painless swelling of cervical lymph node, usually single. The lymph node is usually freely movable, firm and painless.
Ingestion of alcohol may result in the pain of the diseased lymph node.
</Hodgekin-lymphoma> 

<post-anasthesia-care-unit>
Priority is to maintain ABCs upon reiceval, second priority to to monitor the incision site, third is giving presribed meds.
</post-anasthesia-care-unit>

<urinalysis>
The sample does not need to be sterile. 
If obtaining from a catheter, use sterile technique to not introduce infection into the catheter, but the sample itself doens't need to be sterile. 
</urinalysis> 

<tardive-dyskinesia>
Characterized by abnormal facial or tongue movements. Treated by decreasing or discontinuing antipsychotic medication. Symptoms may reverse however may be permanent as well.
</tardive-dyskinesia>

<pseudoparkinsonism>
Symptoms that mimic Parkinson's syndrome such as shuffling gait, tremors and rigidity. Treated with anticholinergics. 
</pseudoparkinsonism>

<acute-dystonic-reaction>
Caused by too much cholinergic neurotransmitters compared to dopaminergic ones. Contraction of facial and neck muscles, treated with diphenhydramine or benzotropine. Symtpoms improve after 10-30 min after administering IV anticholinergics. 
</acute-dystonic-reaction>

<neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>
Life threatening reaction that is lethal in 10% of cases.
Stop the medication. Cool the body, administer bromocriptine to treat muscle regidity, dantrolene to reduce muscle spasms.
</neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>

<dantrolene>
Used for muscle spasms, and it coudld be used for malignant hypothermia. 
</dantrolene>

<infant>
Ages below 1 year.
Erikson - Trust vs Mistrust
</infant>

<toddler>
Ages 1 - 3
Erikson - Autonomy vs Shame and Doubt
Speaks in sdgments of 3-4 words.
Able to express likes and dislikes. 
Assertion of independence
Understand cuasality.

Encourage parents: postive reinforcement, give simple rationals, provide two selections for choice
Communication: 
12months - gestures (pointing, waving), follows one step commands, single words.
24 months - repeats words and phrases (echolalia), combines 2-3 words together, impulsive (tantrums), vocabulary of 40-50 words.
36 months - multiple words into pharases, verbalizes name, age and gender. Short conversations, follow 3 step commands, vocabulary of 200-1000 words.
</toddler>

<pre-schooler>
Ages 3 - 5
Erikson - Initiative vs Guilt
Uses complete sentences. 
Could perform simple chores like putting away toys, or gringing items to the table.
Understands right from wrong.
</pre-schooler>

<school-age>
Age 5-13
Erikson - Industry vs. Inferiority
</school-age>

<teenager>
Ages 13-21
Erikson - Identity vs Role Confusion
</teenager>

<young-adult>
Ages 21-39
Erikson - Intimacy vs Isolation.
</young-adult>

<middle-aged-adult>
Ages 40-65
Erikson - Generativty vs Stagnation
</middle-aged-adult>

<older-adult>
Ages 65+
Erikson - Integrity vs Despair
</older-adult>

<detached-retina>
Symptoms: floaters across field of vision, blurred vision, black curtain over visual field

Surgery: scleral buckling or laser photocoagulation

Post operatively:
Limit eye movement of both eyes (even with sureger on one eye), bed rest with eye patch over operated eye.
May require special positioning to maintain intravitreal bubble. 
Give eye drops - antibiotics, antiinflammatory and dilating agenets.
</detached-retina>

<lactulose>
Traps and expells ammonia from the blood via the feces. Results in soft formed stools.
Also used as a laxative. 
</lactulose>

<doppler-ultrasound>
Probe held at 45 degrees.
Probe should be held lightly as to not obliterate the pulse. If movement is performed move distal to proximal.
Gel should be warm to reduce vasoconstriction.
</doppler-ultrasound>

<pulse-deficit>
Difference between apical and peripheral pulses.    
</pulse-deficit>

<thiazide-diuretics>
Examples: Chlorothiazide, hydrochlorothiazide, indapamide, chlorthalidone, metolazone. 
Act directly on the kidney to inhibit the sodium/chloride cotransporter - which has a function of reabsorbing sodium and chloride ions in DCT.
Increase sodium secretion.
Increase potassium secretion.
Decrease calcium secretion, thereby increasing serum calcium.
Promotes alkalosis by increasing the release of hydrogen through urine.
</thiazide-diuretics>

<histrionic-disorder>
Overreaction to events.
</histrionic-disorder>

<electro-convulsive-therapy>
Good candidate: pregnant, suicidal or catatonic, major depression, bipolar mania and schitzophrenia. 
Contraindications: cardiac problems, osteoporosis, loose teeth. 
2-3 tretments per week for a month or 6-12 sessions total
Performed under anesthesia
</electro-convulsive-therapy>

<central-line-associated-bloodstream-infection>
In order to get accurate cultures, first collect blood cultures from two separate peripheral sites then begin empiric antibiotic therapy with broad spectrum AB right away without waiting for cultures to return.  
</central-line-associated-bloodstream-infection>

<non-tunneled-central-venous-access-device>
Used for a short term, in acute care settings.
Insertion procedure:
Full sterile field with gowns, caps and masks and patient is covered with full body sterile drapes. 
Patient is placed in Trandelenburg position (head down) to contain air emboli in lower chambers and to produce dilation of neck and subclavian veins. 
Subclavian vein is used most of the time. Sometimes basilic, cephalic or as a last resort femoral veins could be used.
Area is swabbed with chlorhexidine to remove any residual oils. 
Patient is asked to turn head away from insertion site to give more tension. 
Lidocaine is injected into tissue to numb the area.
Large bore needle is insertered parallel to the clavicle and guided deeper until it hits the vein.
Patient is asked to take a deep breath and perform the Valsalva manuver, that is bear down, to create a positive pressure phase in central venous pressure and make it harder for air emboli to move in, as the cather is guided through the needle and into the superior vena cava. 
Needle is removed and catheter is sutured to the skin.
Chlorhexidine impregnated gauze with transparent dressing is placed over the insertion site.
Catheter placement is confirmed with an x-ray (as well as to rule out accidental puncture of the pleura and pneumothorax) 
</non-tunneled-central-venous-access-device>

<glucocorticoids>
Increase in times of stress. 
</glucocorticoids>

<Addisons-disease>
Autoimmune disorders that results in destruction of adrenal glands. 
All three corticoids are reduced: glucocorticoids (cortisol), mineralcorticoids (aldosterone), and androgens. 
Lifelong steroid homrones given, doses should be increased during stresses like surgery.
Salt is added to the diet. 
Potassium is usually elevated.
</Addisons-disease>

<Addisonian-crisis>
Due to rapid withdrawl of corticosteroid medication, or stress factors.
Symptoms: hypotension, tachycardia, electrolyte imbalances.
Can lead to shock and circulatory collapse. 
</Addisonian-crisis>

<adrenal-gland>
Zona glomerulose - mineralcorticoid - aldosterone
Zona fasciculada - glucocorticoids - cortisol
Zona reticularis - androgens
Medulla - catecholamines - epinephrine and norepinephrine
</adrenal-gland>

<lactation>
Need to add 400-500 cal daily to pre-pregnancy caloric intake to compensate for breasfeeding.
</lactation>

<multiple-sclerosis>
Avoid overexposure to heat or cold - may damage areas that have lost sensation. May excerbate MS symptoms.
</multiple-sclerosis>

<Paget-disease>
Interferes with bone remodeling, causes enlarged skull, curving of leg bones, bones become weaker.
Elevated serum alkaline phosphatase (ALP).
Treated with same medications as osteoporosis (biphosphonates).
</Paget-disease>

<overdose>
Check for responsiveness and breathing rate - if none begin CPR
Call for nearby helps
Have someone call 911
Have someone get AED 
Have someone get nalaxone
</overdose>

<opioid-withdrawl>
shivering, abdominal cramping, muscle and bone pain, vomiting, diarrhea. 
</opioid-withdrawl>

<GTPAL>
Gravida - number of pregnancies (twins or more count as one)
Term - number of deliveries of 38 weeks + (twins or more count as one)
Preterm - number of deliveries 20 - 37 weeks (twins or more count as one)
Abortions - number of pregnancies ending prior to 20 weeks (including spontaneously) (twins or more count as 1)
Living - number of living children 
</GTPAL>

<gravida-parity>
Only uses two numbers
Gravida - number of pregnancies (twins or more count as one)
Parity - number of pregnancies carried past 20 weeks, including pregncies that eneded in spontaneous abortion. (Also counts multiple embryos as one)
</gravida-parity>

<intestinal-secretions>
Hihgh in bicarbonate, loss of which (like in iliostomys) leads to metabolic acidosis
</intestinal-secretions>

<metabolic-acidosis>
Associated with hyperkalemia, Kussmaul respirations (deep rapid breathing to rid body of CO2) and tachycardia.
</metabolic-acidosis>

<eating-disorders>
Observe the client before, during and after meals.
Avoid discussions about food especially while eating.
Require food consumption within limited amount of time.
Feed through an NG tube if required.
</eating-disorders>

<Haemophilus-influenzae>
Leading cause of bacterial meningitis in children under 5 years old. Could also cause pneumonia, sepsis and death. 
</Haemophilus-influenzae>

<delivery-instructions>
Panting through the mouth helps prevent immediate delivery. Confirm that the neonate doesn't have a cord around the neck before proceeding with delivery. If cord is detected slip two fingers between it and the neonate to give space for breathing and continue with delivery.
</delivery-instructions>

<cervix-dilation>
5cm/hour in nulliparous women
10cm/hour in multiparous women
</cervix-dilation>

<basal-cell-carcinoma>
Most common type of skin cancer.
Most are located on face and neck.
Sometimes donut shaped pearly papule with a waxy border.
Most are localized and do not metastasize. 
</basal-cell-carcinoma>

<actinic-keratosis>
Small papule with rough, dry, scaly skin.
</actinic-keratosis>

<squamous-cell-carcinoma>
Firm nodular lesion covered by crust.
</squamous-cell-carcinoma>

<ciprofloxacin>
Class of drugs known as fluoroquinolones.
Milk, yougurt and ceffeine interferes with medication absorption, avoid taking together with the medicine. Could be consumed in between doses though.
Calcium could alter absorption and should not be taken within 6 hours of the medication. 
Could be taken with or without meals.
Increase in fluid intake is required to prevent crystalluria and renal calculi, cipro increases the risk for both. 
May cause increased sensitivity to sun.
</ciprofloxacin>

<meconium>
Usually passed within 24 hours.
</meconium>

<newborn-respiratory-rate>
Normal is 30 - 60 breaths per minute.
</newborn-respiratory-rate>

<pregnancy-low-back-pain>
Intermittened low back pain could indicate overly distended uterus and could be a sign of oncoming labor. Especially if there are multiple fetuses.
</pregnancy-low-back-pain>

<false-labor>
Contractions are irregular and don't get closer together.
Don't start from the back and radiate through the abdomen, unlike in true labor. Usually the pain is only felt in the front.
Contractions stop with relaxation.
</false-labor>

<chemical-stress-test>
Medications most commonly used: 
Dipyridamole thallium 201
Adenosine
Dobutamine
IV medications given to clients to simulate a stress test on the heart when client is unable to do physical activity.
A sonogram is performed to detect any abnormalities.
</chemical-stress-test>

<mixing-insulin>
Done to avoid giving the patient multiple injections if they require both short term and extended action insulin injections.
Most commonly mixed insulins are regular and NPH (Neutral Protamine Hagedorn)
Never mix insulin Glargine (Lantus) with any other insulin.
Administer the injection within 5-10 min after drawing it up because regular insulin binds to NPH and decreases the action (of regular insulin).
Why does the order matter: NPH insulin should not be introduced into regular insulin vial because of the binding effect.
</mixing-insulin>

<tendonitis>
Treatment is applying ice, resting and analgesics.
</tendonitis>

<end-of-life>
Clients often times refuse fluids in last days, effects of dehydration take a toll on the mind.
Clients could experience restlessness, agitation and hallucinations.
</end-of-life>

<effects-of-aging>
Decreased pain tolerance.
</effects-of-aging>

<colorectal-cancer>
Risk factors: obesity, smoking, alcohol, physical inactivity and diet.
Other risk factors: Age (45+), Race(African-American and Eastern Jewish), Type II Diabetes 
</colorectal-cancer>

<nutrition-fat>
Saturated and trans: solid at room temperature, found in animal tallow
Places: butter, pork, chicken and beef fat, cakes, nuts, chips, tropical plant oils (coconut, palm etc.), margerine 
</nutrition-fat>

<adult-diaper>
To ensure proper fit front absorbent matt should come to the naval
Change diaper after 20 ounces of absorbency is reached or after 2 wettings, usually 2-3 times per day.
Avoid wearing a large diaper to avoid frequent changes.
Use a barrier cream such as zinc oxide after each diaper change.
</adult-diaper>

<urge-incontinence> 
Also called overactive bladder
Sudden urge to urinate with no control
Often due to damage to the nerves 
</urge-incontinence>

<stress-urinary-incontinence>
Release of urine when bladder is physically stressed (pressed) from physical activity, jumping, laughing, sneezing etc.
</stress-urinary-incontinence>

<neurogenic-shock>
Loss of sympathetic tone. 
Most common cuase is damage to the spinal column above T6 
Symptoms are dry, warm skin, low bp and maybe brady cardia.
</neurogenic-shock>

<games-by-age>
Toddler (1.5-3) - picture books, pounding board, regular household items, manu opportunities for exploration, 4 - 12 piece wood puzzles, blocks, cars, crayons, large paintbrush, dolls, balls, push-pull toys, rocking horses.
Pre-Schooler (3-5) - dress up clothes, tricycle, skates.
</games-by-age>

<hypokalemia>
Muscle weakness, especially in the legs. Parasthesia in the hands.
</hypokalemia>

<why-questions>
Don't ask why questions - they are confrontational.
</why-questions>

<Guillain-Barre-Syndrome>
Ascending paralysis that starts with tingling in feet and could paralyze the body, including breathing and swallowing.
Could be triggered by a viral or a bacterial infection.
Autoimmune condition which affects the myelination of the nerves.
Treatments could include plasma exchange and immunoglobulin therapy.
Has no effect on cognitive function.
Recovery happens in 90% of cases but usually takes several months to a few years.
</Guillain-Barre-Syndrome>

<central-venous-access>
Femoral site has a higher chance for infection, femoral site is only used if subclavian site is unavailble.
</central-venous-access>

<tuberculosis>
Endemic in certain parts of asia, people from Asian countries should be screened for it.
</tuberculosis>

<fundus-decension>
Rate of 1cm per day, after 10 days should be below the pubic bone.
Subinvolution could cause hemorrhage. 
</fundus-decension>

<lochia>
Rubra - 1 to 4 days after birth, small blood clots not larger than plum are normal
Serosa - pink to brown discharge, 4-10 days after delivery
Alba - yellow whitish discharge from 10 - 14 days. 
</lochia>

<postpartum-assessment>
Massage boggy uterus. 
Monitor for thrombophlebitis in legs, ambulate.
</postpartum-assessment>

<brain-lobes>
parietal - sensation and orientation in space
temporal - audio processing
occipital - visual
frontal - higher order fuctions, personality, speech, emotions.
</brain-lobes>

<dementia-bathing>
Sing or talk continuously to help the client relaxation.
Expose only one area at a time to keep warm and provide privacy
Bathe slowly and explain every step.
</dementia-bathing>

<cardio-pulmonary-resucitation>
Assess for responsiveness - make sure the patient is not sleeping or easily roused
Activate emergency response- shout to someone to call 911
Check the pulse as you scan for signs of life - if yes check breathing if no got to next step
Begin chest compressions
After 30 compressions open the airway and give two breaths
Resume compressions at rate of 30:2 
</cardio-pulmonary-resucitation>

<libel>
Writing false information about someone
</libel>

<prenatal-diagnostics>
Glucose tolerance test
HIV test
Hep B test
Blood typing
STI test
</prenatal-diagnostics>

<maternal-serum-alpha-fetoprotein>
Blood test given to the mother at 15-20 weeks (second trimester)
Assesses for neural tube defects (such as spina bifida or ananecephaly) and other chromosomal abnormalities.
</maternal-serum-alpha-fetoprotein>

<bone-marrow-biopsy>
Using bones such as iliac crest or sternum
Could result in heavy bleeding due to deep penetration of tissue.
</bone-marrow-biopsy>

<anxiety>
Anxiety is a normal response to stress.
Management of anxiety is geared with learning to cope with existing experiences, not seeking out new ones to "conquer" anxiety.
Calling the therapis every time there is some anxiety is not recommended since the patient might become too reliant on them.
</anxiety>

<furosemide>
Potassium wasting diuretic.
</furosemide>

<spironolactone>
Potassium sparing diuretic.
</spironolactone>



<phenozopyridine>
Causes urine to become organge or red, which is normal.
If the kidneys cannot excrete it fast enough then the skin could become dislored too, in which case the med should be stopped immediately. 
</phenozopyridine>

<post-partum>
It's normal to urinate up to 3000ml per day for 2-3 days post, as fluid accumulated during pregnancy is leaving the body.
</post-partum>

<Naegeles-rule>
Determine first day of last menstrual period
Subtract 3 calendar months from that time
Add 7 days
</Naegeles-rule>

<fundal-height>
Increases by 1cm/week starting at 12-14 weeks and lasts until 36 weeks, then it varies.
Rises just above the pubis symphysis at about 12-14 weeks.
</fundal-height>

<colostomy>
Rinsing or reusing the ostomy pouch is not recommended. 
Do not reduce fluid intake to make the stool harder.
</colostomy>

<pacemakers>
Hearing aid may affect placement of the transmitter, as it shouldn't come within 6 inches of it.
Avoid placing devices that are battery operated or magnetic close to the transmitter.
Do not stay close near anti-theft devlices (like metal detecotrs) walk through them at a normal pace.
Avoid welding equipment, large generators, radar towers, and MRIs.
Usually place in upper left chest or under left clavicle. 
Electrical equipment that is grounded and well mantained is ok.
Common house appliances like microwaves, remotes, electric blankets will not affect the pacemaker.
</pacemakers>

<Dupuytrens-contracture>
Thickening of skin near the base of the palm which causes fingers to contract towards the wrist or deflect.
Most often affects ring and pinky fingers.
Treatment includes surgery, using a needle to break the tissue and enzyme injections to soften the tissue.
Most commonly associated with middle age (50+) men of Scandinavian or Celtic descnet and is assaociated with diabetes, gout, arthritis and alcoholism.
</Dupuytrens-contracture>

<Duchenne-muscular-dystrophy>
Genetic disorder characterizide by progressive muscle degeneration.
Typically found in boys.
Starts around ages 2-3, affects the legs first, affects the heart and breathing muscles later.
Life expectancy is around 16 to early 20s.
</Duchenne-muscular-dystrophy>

<cataracts>
After surgery: avoid increasing IOP, avoid sleeping on affected side, wear an eye patch at night and glasses durinig the day, avoid getting water in the eye, avoid prolonged reading or eye strain.
</cataracts>

<packed-red-blood-cells>
Administered with 18G catheter.
Should be administered in less than 4 hours to prevent bacterial contamination.
</packed-red-blood-cells>

<loop-diuretic>
Examples: furosemide, bumetanide, torsemide
They are potassium wasting. 
</loop-diuretic>

<interpersonal-behviour>
Do not ask why questions, they are confrontational even before the facts are known.
Do involve emotional aspects into your questions as they are also confrontational.
</interpersonal-behviour>

<aspirin>
Could be taken alongside clopidogrel.
</aspirin>

<hepatitis-a>
Fecal-oral route.
Not transmitted through the blood.
Traveling to high to medium level affected couintries such as Africa, South America, and Asia.
</hepatitis-a>

<blood-pressure>
Optimal position for measuring BP is sitting upright. Laying down may incrase the reading by as much as 8 mmHg
</blood-pressure>

<dehydration>
Dry skin, tachycardia, cold extremities.
</dehydration>

<lithium>
Early toxicity includes symptoms of nausea, vomiting and diarrhea
Severe toxicity is characterized by ataxia, confusion and seizures. 
</lithium>

<carbohydrates>
Increase the production of CO2, avoid in respiratory compromised clients.
</carbohydrates>

<dose-adjustment>
Must be verified by two nurses for important medications like insulin and heparin.
</dose-adjustment>

<theraputic-communication>
If client is experiencing a concern about an issue, first normalize the experience, then explain what to do about the actual issue.
</theraputic-communication>

<seizure>
Loosen clothing, place pillow under the head, place clinet on side with head flexed forward and down so that saliva could drain and tongue can roll forward.
</seizure>

<hypocalcemia>
Numbness in the fingertips
</hypocalcemia>

<colorectal-cancer>
Screening: colonoscopy every 10 years after age of 45, if barium enema is selected for screen should be done every 5 years, if fecalt occult blood 
is selected as screening method it should be done every year.
</colorectal-cancer>

<Hegars-sign>
Softening of the cervix, indicative of pregnancy, palpated on a bimanual exam.
Sign is present from 4th week until the 12th week of pregnancy.
</Hegars-sign>

<quickening>
First movement of the fetus, usually occurs in 18th or 20th week of pregnancy.
</quickening>

<positive-sign-of-pregnancy>
Auscultation of fetal heart beat, which can usually be first auscultated at 12 weeks.
</positive-sign-of-pregnancy>

<deep-vein-thrombosis>
Massage is contraindicated in clients that are at an increased risk for DVT, due to the possibility of dislodging the thrombus. Sequantial pressure device should instead be used. 
</deep-vein-thrombosis>

<African-American>
Higher risk of colorectal cancer and lung cancer.
</African-American>

<unlicensed-assistive-personal>
Can collect stool samples and measure and record blood-pressure.
</unlicensed-assistive-personal>

<malpractice> 
A type of negligence where a there is a failure to act as a competent person would normally act in that situation. Does not have to be intentional.
Requres four elements to be proven, the four Ds : Damages - Injury is present, Direct cause - cuasation is present, Duty - had the duty to care for the person at the moment, dereliction - breach of duty
Examples: improper use of equipment, failure to act in emergency, inapropriate medication administration.
</malpractice>

<cluster-headaches>
One of the most painful types of headaches. Occur in one side of the head.
Acute treatment is to provide 100% oxygen at 6-8L/min for 10 min. May be repeated after a 5 min rest.
Oxygen causes vasoconstriction and increases the synthesis of serotonin in the central-nervous-system.
Sumatriptan could be given.
</cluster-headaches>

<crutches>
Should be 2 inches below armpits.
</crutches>

<colostomy>
Assess the new stoma every 4 hours post surgery.
</colostomy>

<oral-suctioning>
Tonsil tip (Yanakur) cather is used.
</oral-suctioning>

<laryngectomy-suctioning>
Only performed as necessary to prevent complications.
Suction laryngectomy tube first, then mouth to prevent contamination.
</laryngectomy-suctioning>

<diabetic-ketoacidosis>
Plyuria - body is trying to get rid of excess sugar
Hypotension - as a result of dehydration
</diabetic-ketoacidosis>

<chemotherapy-precautions>
Medications remain in the client's body for 3-7 days.
Clinets who recieved chemo in the last 48 hours shold be under chemotherapy precautions.
Wear two pairs of chemotherapy approved gloves, one on top of the other.
When contacting the client, linens, or fluids also wear a special gown.
Hands must always be washed with soap after removal of ppe.
Flush toilet twice after disposing of fluids.
</chemotherapy-precautions>

<standard-precautions>
Hand hygine
Use of proper PPE for the procedure.
Sharps safety.
</standard-precautions>

<droplet-precautions>
Mask on patient when transporting.
Single room or room with similarly infected.
Could leave door open (droplets fall on floor after expiration).
</droplet-precautions>

<Addisons-disease>
Sodium wasting, potassium saving - lack of aldosterone and cortisol results in hyperkalemia. 
Dehydration and hypovolemia could trigger Addisonian-crisis.
Simple stress could execerbate symptoms (due to lack of cortisol, which helps the body respond to stress).
Results in a destruction of the adrenal cortex.
Lack of cortisol increases insulin production and reduces glucose production causing hypoglycemia.
Lack of cortisol decreases sensitivity to catecholamines, causing hypotension.
Lack of immune response causes infections.
</Addisons-disease>

<aldosterone>
Functions to retain sodium and excrete potassium.
</aldosterone>

<cortisol>
Increases release of glucose and decreases insulin production. 
Increases sensistivity to chatecolemines. 
</cortisol>

<antisocial-personality-disorder>
Provide safety for other clients.
Establish and enforce limits.
Avoid making deals.
Anger can be used to manipulate.
</antisocial-personality-disorder>

<toilet-training>
Four signs to indicate readiness:
waking up dry from a nap
being aware of the urge
communicating the need to go
being dry for at least 2 hours during the day

Bowel control is established before urinary control.

Bed wetting is normal in girls until 4yo and in boys until 5yo. Alert the doctor if child doesn't achieve control by 6yo.
Night time bladder control occurs a few months after day time control is achieved.

Provide a potty chair rather than having to start with a toilet and allows the child to place feet on floor.

Avoid long training sessions, limit to 5-10 min in the bathroom.
</toilet-training>



<nasal-canula>
Maximum flow rate is at 6L/min
FiO2 22-44%
</nasal-canula>

<simple-face-mask>
Minimal flow rate 6L/min (any lower and the client will rebreath) maximum 8L/min
FiO2 - 40-60%
</simple-face-mask>

<partial-rebreather-mask>
Has a two way valve between the bag and the mask, mask has no openings into the atmosphere.
Flow rate 6-8L/min
FiO2 60-80%
</partial-rebreather-mask>

<non-rebreather-mask>
Has a one way valve between mask and bag and a one way valve to the atmosphere.
Flow rate 10-15L/min
FiO2 - 60-90%
</non-rebreather-mask>

<venturi-mask>
Flow rate 2-15L/min
FiO2 - precise 24-60%
</venturi-mask>

<foreign-body-airway-obstruction>
Never perform a blind finger sweep of mouth - can push the object further down. 
In infants <1 years: Alternate 5 back blows and 5 chest compressions until object clears or infant becomes unresponsive.
Children 1 - 8: Heimligh manuver until unresponsive.
If none of these work: begin direct rigid bronchoscopy.
If the object can not be removed - if it is above vocal chords - perform a cricothyrotomy, if below then et tube.
</foreign-body-airway-obstruction>

<infectious-mononucleosis>
Kissing disease. Caused by Epstein-Barr virus.
Passed from person to person through saliva, but no extra precautions beyond standard need to be used.
</infectious-mononucleosis>

<bacterial-pneumonia>
Not infectious - could share rooms.
</bacterial-pneumonia>

<herpes-zoster>
Shingles.
Requires airborne and contact precautions. Observed until the lesions are dry and crusted. 
</herpes-zoster>

<hemodialysis>
Hold antihypertensives - could lower BP too much
Hold antibiotics - will be removed with dialysate
Do not hold insulin
Do not hold pain medication
</hemodialysis>

<cushing-disease>
High protein diet to minimize muscle wasting.
Low carb diet to not gain weight.
Low calorie diet.
High potassium diet because of high potassium excretion by the kidney.
</cushing-disease>

<bladder-cancer>
Associated strong with smoking.
Not associated with alcohol consumption.
</bladder-cancer>

<enteral-nutrition>
Air in line could cause flatulance.
Incorrect temperature can cause diarrhea.
Too much residual indiciates slow digestion and could cause nausea. 
</enteral-nutrition>

<patient-education>
Do not ask "Do you understand or do you have any question"? - Patient maybe be uncomfortable in answer yes to those. 
Say "tell me about" or "What questions do you have?"
Do not ask simple yes or no questions.  
</patient-education>

<Holter-monitor>
Stay away from electrical devices. 
</Holter-monitor>

<broken-arm>
Evaluate a neurovascular status of the extremity, apply ice, then splint and elevate. 
</broken-arm>

<meconium-in-utero>
Suction mouth and nose with a bulb syringe.
No need to suction the trachea.
</meconium-in-utero>

<reynold-syndrome>
Blood vessel constriction with stress or cold, usually effects the nose and fingers.
Treatment isn't needed. 
</reynold-syndrome>

<theophylline>
Used as tablets to control asthma, by relaxing airway muscles.
Theraputic range is 10-20 mcg/ml of blood. Toxicity is over 20 mcg/ml
</theophylline>

<digoxin>
Normal levels is between 0.5 - 2ng/ml
</digoxin>

<lithium>
Theraputic range for initial management is 1 - 1.5 mEq. Management doses are lower at 0.8 - 1.2 mEq/L .
</lithium>

<wet-to-dry-dressing>
Usually requires pain medication.
Used as a method of debridment, lower layers dry and pull of eschar.
Remove old tape - pull parallel to skin, towards the dressing.
</dressing-change>

<feeding-tube>
During insertion if patient is coughing the tube is in the trachea, remove the tube and let patinet rest before attempting reinsertion.
</feeding-tube>

<peritoneal-dialysis>
Abdominal pain is common during the first few exchanges. It's due to peritonieal irritation. It usually subsides in 1 to 2 weeks of treatment.
</peritoneal-dialysis>

<vegan-diet>
Lack vitamin D, Calcium from dairy and Vit B12, and Iron from meats.
Have vitamin B1 and A which are found in vegies.
</vegan-diet>

<pregnancy-nausea>
Associated with an increase in human chorionic gonadotropin hormone.
Could start as early as 4 weeks.
Should diminish by 14th week of pregnancy.
Eating a dry carbohydrate immediately upon arising.
Eating more protein with an evening meal might help, like a bedtimes snack of penut butter or cheese.
Eat salty or sour food (potato chips or lemonade) during periods of nausea.
Consume ginger foods or teas.
Don't brush teeth immediately after eating.
Do not delay meals, excessive hunger could cause nausea. 
Avoid consuming fluids early in the day, during nausea or after meals.
</pregnancy-nausea>

<asthma>
For kids, give the inhaler and spacer to nurse not teacher and don't have them carry it with them. 
</asthma>

<sudden-vaginal-bleeding>
Ask when the first day of last period was to determine if it's a possible spontaneous abortion.
Ask when bleeding started to estimate blood loss.
</sudden-vaginal-bleeding>

<statin>
Common side effects: rash, headach, GI disturbances.
Important side effect: muscle pain or tenderness - could indicate myositis or muscle inflammation which could lead
to rhabdomyolysis, which could lead to kidney failure.
</statin>

<paracentesis>
Removal of fluid from the abdomen.
Positioned in a supine position with head of bed slightly elevated.
</paracentesis>

<pheochromocytoma>
Benign tumor of the adrenal glands, causes hypertension.
</pheochromocytoma>

<pre-filled-syringe>
Do not expell the air bubble. It prevents leakage by pushing the medicine into the tissue.
</pre-filled-syringe>

<social-readjustment-rating-scale>
Rates life events on a scale of most stressful to least, some common ones:

Death of a spouce (100)
Divorce (76)
Jail Term (63)
Death of close family member (63)
Fired at work (47)
Foreclosure (30)
Children leaving home (29)
Trouble with boss (23)
Minor violation of the law (11)
</social-readjustment-rating-scale>

<beginning-of-labor>
Bloody show - vaginal discharge with a little blood indicates the end of pregnancy and begnning of labor.
Contractions are felt in lower black 
Fetal movement decreases
</beginning-of-labor>

<personal-protective-equipment>
Remove the PPE just prior (not after) existing the containemnt room.
</personal-protective-equipment>

<lower-back-pain>
Best position for pain relief is in bed with head levated 45 degrees and knees moderately flexed - flexingin the knees relieves pressure on the sciatic nerve.
Knees should be higher than hips.
</lower-back-pain>

<informed-concent>
Should be obtained from next of kin or spouce if the client is not mentally competent.
</informed-concent>

<heel-pressure-injury>
Place a roll under calf, not under achilles tendon as that will cause injury.
Wear socks when in bed to reduce injury from friction.
Do not massage the area as that will increase tissue breakdown.
</heel-pressure-injury>

<crutches>
Should be kept 8-10 inches to the side.
Elbows flexed at 20-30 degrees.
</crutches>

<incident-report>
Do not document the fact that incident report was filed in the client's health record.
</incident-report>

<post-anesthesia>
Fine crackles are an expected finding. 
</post-anesthesia>

<A1C-hemoglobin>
Normal levels are 4-6%
</A1C-hemoglobin>

<calcium>
Protein bound, so with low protein calcium could be low as well.
</calcium>

<wound-healing>
Monitor albumin (norm: 3.5-5) and total protein.
Adequate intake of protein, vitamin C and zinc.
Foods such as meat (protein and zinc), legumes (zinc), nuts (zinc), dairy (zinc)
</wound-healing>

<oral-steroids>
Are ulcerogenic and should be adminsted with meals.
</oral-steroids>

<pediatric-vitals>
See pediatric_vitals.png chart in the downloads folder.
</pediatric-vitals>

<neonate-ointment>
Usually tetracycline or erythromycin.
Prevents opthalmia neonatorum, caused by gonorrheal or chalmydial infection.
</neonate-ointment>

<atrial-fibrillation>
Could be treateed with amiodarone and digoxin, watch for toxicities such as blurred vision and halos.
</atrial-fibrillation>

<contrast>
If given to renal patient, time with dialysis to immediately remove the contrast from the blood.
Oral contrast could contain a laxative to prevent constipation and promote explusion, so diarrhea is normal after the procedure.
</contrast>

<Addisons-disease>
Hypoglycemia - due to lack of cortisol. 
Hyperpigmentation - caused by excess ACTH
Weight loss - due to continued loss of water
Low blood pressure
</Addisons-disease>

<common-supplements>
Feverfew - used to prevent migranes, interacts with platelet aggregation and so should not be used with aspirin and warfarin/heparin.
Echinacea - used to decrease inflammation and manage infections, suppresses immune system should not be combined with HIV, TB or cancer medications.
Valerian - interacts with depressent meds.
St.John's wort - treats depression, interacts with antidepressants and could cause excess serotonin and serotonin syndrome.
</common-supplements>

<pregnancy-adaptations>
Blood pressure decreases as the pregnancy goes on in response to vasodialating effect of progesterone.
</pregnancy-adaptations>

<pediatric-pain-management>
Neonate - Infant (0-1):  sucrose on the pacifier, swaddling and swaying.
Toddler - Preschooler (1-5): toys books, singing.
School age - video games, tv
</pediatric-pain-management>

<Self-Determination-Act>
Requires providers to provide information to clients about the patient rights, so they can make a decision for themselves.
</Self-Determination-Act>

<omnibus-budget-reconciliation-act>
Provides clients with rights to be free from physical or chimical restraints as a method of discipline or convience. 
</omnibus-budget-reconciliation-act>

<tarasoff-ruling>
Required reporting of planned self harm or harm to others.
</tarasoff-ruling>

<insulin>
Lispro - very fast acting - onset 15-30 min, peak on 30 min to 90 min, duration 3-5 hours.
Regular - onset 30-60min, 1-5 hours peak, duration 6-10 hours.
Neutral Protamine Hagedorn - intermediate acting, peak action of 4-12 hours, duration of 16 hours.
Glargine - onset 3-4 hours, no peak, 24 hours duration.
</insulin>

<kidney-stones>
Calcium oxalate - comes from green leafy vegetalbes, like rhubarb, also cola, tea, chocolate and high doses of vitamin C.
Struvite stones - associated with urinary tract infectionotin, need to acidify the urine by increaseing egg consumption, as well as consumption of fish and cranberries.
Uric acid stones - cut down on foods high in purines such as red meat, organ meats, beer and alcohol, sardines, shellfish.
Cystine stones - caused by a rare disorder which elevates cystine in the blood, urine needs to be more alkaline so consumption of milk, nuts and vegetables needs to be increased. 
</kidney-stones>

<epoetin-alpha>
Hemoglobin should not increase rapidly or above 12 g/dL or the risk of thromboembolytic events increases. 
Once hemoglobin approaches 11 g/dL or if hemoglobin rises by more than 1g/dL in a 2 week period, dosage should be decreased by 25%.
This threshold is lower for clients with chronic-kidney-disease.
</epoetin-alpha>

<hispanic-culture>
Silence is a sign of disagreement.
Direct eye contact is avoided with authority figures.
Prefer social interactions before being asked personal questions.
</hispanic-culture>

<anaphylectic-reaction>
Runny nose and sneezing is indicative of an atopic reacon but not anaphylaxis.
Diffuse rash is not indicative of anaphylaxis and does not happen immediately.
</anaphylectic-reaction>

<heart-failure>
Ejection fraction 55% - 70% Normal level
40-50% - may be asymptomatic
35-39% - mild heart failure, may have dyspnea.
<35% - moderate to severe.
</heart-failure>

<Alzheimers>
Should only cook with supervision.
Don't argue.
Place limits on wrong behaviours.
Focus on feelings rather than words, for example "you seem worried"
</Alzheimers>

<burns>
Monitor hemodynamics frequently and administer fluids to prevent hypovolemic shock.
Diet high in calories, vitamin C, Zinc and protein. 
Daily weights, 2% weight loss from pre burn weight is a mild caloric deficit, over 10% requires modification of intake.
Positing and range of motion exercies.

Totol body surface area:
18% back / 18% front
9% each arm (4.5% back and front)
18% each leg (9% back and front)
9% head (4.5% back and front)
1% perenium
</burns>

<bulemia>
Set eating habits and make a contract.
Monitor for one hour to prevent purging.
</bulemia>

<antihypertensives>
Should be taken in the morning as the meds are most effective when the client is active. 
</antihypertensives>

<restraints>
Never attach them to side rails, must be attached to a stable portion of the bed frame.
</restraints>

<intra-cranial-pressure>
Could affect the gag reflex.
</intra-cranial-pressure>

<tracheostomy>
Track cleaning and care should be done every 8 hours.
During first few days secretions tend to be thick.
Keep a spare of same size or larger at bedside.
Wait 24 hours to chage ties to prevent irritating the trachea.
Changing ties or moving the trach tube could irritate the trachea and cause coughing. 
Suction when there is a moist cough or hypoxia. 
In case of dislodgement, notify physician and respiratory therapist, raise the clients head of bed 
</tracheostomy>

<croup>
Barking cough caused by a virus. Treatment is dexamethasone.
</croup>

<performace-improvement-nurse>
Reports are not meant to get other nurses in trouble or for disciplinary actions.
</performace-improvement-nurse>

<peritonitis>
Adbominal pain and rebound tenderness.
Vomiting, diarrhea and hyperactive bowel sounds.
</peritonitis>

<peritoneal-dialysis>
First indication is a cloudy return dialysate solution.
Requires sterile technique.
</peritoneal-dialysis>

<wet-to-dry-dressing>
Wash hands and prepare your sterile field before removing the old dressing.

Purpose is to absorb drainage and trap debris as the dressing dries.
Dressing must be damp not entirely wet.
Number of layer depened on the depth of the wound.
All wound surfaces have to be in contact with the wet gauze, including dead spaces and tunnels. 
Number of pieces of gauze should be counted and recorded to make sure they're all removed later.
Damp gauze should not touch the skin around the wound.
</wet-to-dry-dressing>

<negative-pressure-wound-therapy>
If pump stops working or falls off, patient should inform the nurse immediately.
NPWT dressing should not be kept on without the pump for more than 2 hours otherwise infection is possible.
Dressing should be removed completely and a wet to dry dressing should be applied until the pump is fixed.
</negative-pressure-wound-therapy>

<implanted-port>
Could swim and shower with it.
Don't need daily flushing.
</implanted-port>

<sodium>
Regular intake should be less than 3,000 mg per day.
Restricted intake should be less than 2,000 mg per day.
Minimum intake is 500 mg per day.
</sodium>

<licensed-nurse-practitioner>
Collecting specimens such as blood, urine and sputum.
Changing wound dressings. 
</licensed-nurse-practitioner>

<respiratory-rate>
Newborn: 25-55 bpm
Infant (6-12mo): 24-30 bpm
Young child (1-5yo): 20-30 bpm
Child(6+): 12-20 bpm
</respiratory-rate>

<heart-rate>
Newborn: 110-160 bpm
Infant (0-1.5): 80-150
Child (1.5 - 11): 70-120
Teen (12+ years) 60-100
</heart-rate>

<blood-pressure>
0-6mo: (65-90)-(45-65) mmHg
6-12mo: (80-100)/(55-65) mmHg
1-11yo: (90-110)/(55-75) mmHg
12+: 120/80 mmHg    
</blood-pressure>

<temperature>
0-3y: 99.4F (37.5C)
3y-5y: 99F (37.2)
5+: 98.6 (37F)
</temperature>

<pulmonary-embolism>
Typically occurs 12-72 hours after injury to a long bone.
Petechia on the chest and mucus membranes.
</pulmonary-embolism>

<deep-vein-thrombosis>
Throbbin pain in the extremity.
Swelling, redness, warmth and pain in the area.
</deep-vein-thrombosis>

<electro-cardio-gram>
Five large squares is 1 second.
Thirty large squares represent 6 seconds.
</electro-cardio-gram>

<surgical-dress-code>
Must wear cap at all times.
Hair should be clipped, not shaved.
Shirt shold be tucked in pants to avoid skin shedding and prevent contact with sterile fields.
Nails should be short and unpolished.
</surgical-dress-code>

<incident-report>
Should be completed even in cases of near misses, where for example a wrong medication was almost given (even though it wasn't)
</incident-report>

<low-fat-diet>
Canadian bacon - considerably leaner than regular bacon and could be incorporated into healthy meals.
</low-fat-diet>

<diabetes>
Rist factors: Race - African American, Hispanic, Native American and Asian 
Age - greater than 45 
Pregnancy - newborn weighing more than 9 lbs
</diabetes>

<breastfeeding>
Newborn should feed every 1.5-3 hours, if not feeding after 3 hours, must awaken the baby and feed.
Breast goes from firm to soft after feeding.
Infant should be heard swollowing.
</breastfeeding>

<diapers>
New borns should have 6-8 wet diapers daily (at least every 4 hours).
</diapers>

<developmental-milestones>
1st - walks without help
2nd - builds a tower of 3-4 blocks
3rd - Uses 2-3 word phrases
4th - Jumps with both feet
</developmental-milestones>

<water-breaking>
Anytime there is a change in labor status the first step is to assess the fetal well being by ausultating the heart rate:
Below 110 - late sign of fetal hypoxia maybe due to a prolapsed cord (when the cord exists the cervix before the baby)
Above 160 - early sign of fetal hypoxia. 

Check for a prolapsed cord.     
Fluid should be straw colored - green or brown fluid should be reported. 
pH of fluid is used to distinguish it from urine - normal pH should be alkaline or 7 and above. 
</water-breaking>

<prolapsed-cord>
Push on the presenting cord to relieve pressure. 
Place the client in Trendelenburg position or knee-chest position. 
</prolapsed-cord>

<autograft>
Usually immobilized and elevated for 3-7 days.
</autograft>

<dopamine>
Used as a vasopressor to increase cardiac output.
</dopamine>

<cast>
Cannot perform range of motion exercises on an extremity with a cast.
Muscle "setting" of the limb in the cast is the best exercies - it's isometric - involves ontracting and releaseing the muscles. 
If a leg is immobilized, quadricept setting must be used to maintain muscle strenght. Maintain contraction for a few seconds for 10 sets. 
Must be done every hour to maintain strenght.   
</cast>

<compartment-syndrome>
Pain, Pulse, Parasthesia, Paralysis, Pale, Poikilothermia (cool extremity) 
</compartment-syndrome>

<chest-tube>
Measured hourly during the first 24 hours after surgery. 
If more than 200 mL of drainage occurs during the first hour and more than 100 mL per hour in the hours after, surgeon should be notified. 
Wall suction must be at least -80mmHg to maintain -20cm H2O in the suction chamber.
Avoid dependent loops 
If chest tube becomes dislodges from the chest, place a dry gauze over the incision and tape on 3 side, making sure to leave one side untaped as to allow relief of pressure.
If the connection becomes dislodged at the chamber level place the end of the tube into 1-2 in of water. 
</chest-tube>

<hip-replacement>
Leg must be abducted in order to maintain proper limb orientation. Use an abductor pillow that's triangle shaped.
</hip-replacement>

<purine>
Shellfish and mussels are high in purine. 
</purine>

<uric-acid>
Avoid oily fish with bones. 
</uric-acid>

<gout>
Caused by uric acid crystals in joints, which is convereted from purine.
Increase fluid intake to over 2L / day
Avoid alcohol and beer as well as high fructose corn syrup.
Avoid organ meats and shellfish. 
</gout>

<common-diseases>
mononucleosis - standard precautions (Epstein-Barr virus) - fatigue, fever and swollen lymph nodes. Spread by saliva. 
hepatitis A - spread by the stool of the person. 
Toxic shock syndrome - cannot be transmitted to others. 
Rhinovirus - common cold, droplet transmission. 
</common-diseases>

<hepatitis>
A - spread through feces
B - all fluids, except feces urine and vomit
C - mostly blood, usually not through sex or feces or urine or vomit. 
D - all fluids, except for feces, urine and vomit.
</hepatitis>

<withdrawl>
Cannabis withdrawl - insomnia, lack of appetite and hyperactivity
Narcotics - watery eyes, cramps and mild tremors. 
Alcohol - hyperalterness, easily startled, anorexia, anxeity, tremors, insomnia, seizures up to 72 hours after last drink, tacticle disturbances (itching, pins and needles etc) 
</withdrawl>

<alcohol-withdrawal>
Use Clinical Institute Withdrawl Assessment for Alcohol, Revise (CIWA-Ar) scale. 
To check for tremors by extending arms and spreading fingers. Even if not visible touch fingertip to feel for vibration. 
Scale checks for N/V: 0-7 points
Tremor: 0-7 points
Sweating: 0-7 points
Agitation: 0-7 points
Tactile distrubances: 0-7
Auditory disturbance: 0-7
Visual distrubances: 0-7
Headache: 0-7
Orientation: 0-4

Total: 0-67
<9: very mild
10-15: mild
16-20: modest
21-67: severe withdrawl

Check cerum electrolytes and coagulation along with CBC
Other symptoms are tachycardia and hypertension
</alcohol-withdrawal>

<risperidone>
Can cause photosensitivity and impaired temperature regulation. 
Can cause orthostatic hypotension. 
Dry mouth
</risperidone> 

<akathesia> 
Inability to remain still. 
</akathesia>

<ectopic-pregnancy>
Unilateral, dull abdominal pain. 
Could present as reffered should pain due to the blood irritating the subdiaphragmatic phrenic nerve.
Could be fatal to the woman due to potential rupture of the fellopian tube and hemorrhage.  
</ectopic-pregnancy>

<threatened-abortion>
Symptoms are spotting and cramping. 
</threatened-abortion>

<spontaneous-abortion>
Frank, red bleeding and moderate cramps.
</spontaneous-abortion>

<normal-effects-of-pregnancy>
Whitish vaginal secretions during the first trimester of pregnancy are normal. 
Breast tenderness and amenorrhea.
</normal-effects-of-pregnancy>

<hyperemesis-gravidum>
Excessive nausea and vomiting.
Could be a sign of hydatidiform mole, due to high levels of hCg
</hyperemesis-gravidum>

<infant-apnea>
Sessation of breathing for more than 20 seconds or if shorter but accompanied by bradycardia, cyanosis, or marked hypotonia. 
Sessation of breathing for periods of less than 20 seconds with no complicating factors is considered normal in neonates, it's called periodic breathing. 
Diagnosis is much more common in preterm infants, and rare in full term.
When it's diagnosed in full term infants, it's usually indicative of an underlying issue. 
</infant-apnea>

<neonate>
Report fever greater than 101F (38.3C)
More than one episode of projectile vomiting should be reported as it's not normal. 
</neonate>

<pneumonia>
Risk factors are underlying lung conditions, shallow breathing due to broken ribs (lack of lung expansion causes pneumonia), anything that decreases lung expansion like bed rest. 
</pneumonia>

<therapy>
Flooding - rapid desensitization where the person is suddenly introduced to the feared subject to learn how to handle it. 
Cognitive Behaviour Therapy - attempts to explain how the persons interpretations and perceptions influences behaviour. 
Psychodynamic therapy - examining past events to see how they reflect the future or current status of the client. 
Psychoterapy - based on Freud that sexual energy drives developement. Use of free association, dream analysis - disocovers the source of repressed thoughts to resolve current conflicts. 
Erikson - focuses on acheiving healthy psychosocial developmental milestones as defined by Erikson. 
Maslow - focus on the whole person, focus on the current situation and solve the problems one level at a time. 
</therapy>

<transfusion-related-lung-injury>
Rare but serious syndrome characterized by acute respiratory difficulty following a transfusion (either immediately during or up to 6 hours after).
Rapid onset of dyspnea and drop of SpO2 < 90%
High morbidity with majority of the patients requiring ventialtor support. 
Lung injury is usually transient and resolve within 48-96 hours with supportive care. 
Could occur due to the client's antibodies activating donor's leukocytes or donor's antibodies activating client lekocytes. 
Leads to sequestration of hyperactive neutrophils along the lung epithelium which leads to pulmonary edema. 
To reduce the risk give, leukocyte reduced blood. 
In case of an event, obtain HLA (human leukocyte antibody) blood test, chest x-ray, oxygen, corticosteroids. Have intubation equipment ready. 
</transfusion-related-lung-injury>

<blood-transfusion>
Reduced leukocyte blood products are given to those that expereinced a transfusion reaction before.
Diphenhydramine, acetaminophen and hydrocortisone is given to clients with high risk of rejection. 
</blood-transfusion>

<apnea-monitor>
White and Black lead - upper right chest and upper left chest
Green lead - on abdomen, not over bony area. 
</apnea-monitor>

<infant-sleep>
Do not use soft mattresses due to increased risk of SIDS, use a firm mattress. 
Do not use bumper guards for same reason.
Do not rock the baby to sleep as that introduces dependence. Instead place them in the crib and let them fall asleep. 
Sleep pattern should be developed by 4 months of age. 
Sleep should last 9-11 hours. 
Total daily sleep should be about 15 hours. 
</infant-sleep>

<preoperative-medication-hold>
Hold all medications that effect hydration and bleeding times. 
Hold diuretics as they increase the risk for hypovolemia and hypokalemia. 
Hold anticoagulats to reduce the risk of severe bleeding. 
</preoperative-medication-hold>

<bulimia-nervosa>
A vicious cycle where the client diets and then binge eats a large quantity of food, then attempts to rid of the food by endusing vomiting. 
Focus is to interrup the cycle. Altering dysfunctional thoughts. Exploring self-concept.
Set limits on eating - like only at a table or with others.
Weight is usually in the normal range. 
Usually aware of the problem and are ashamed.
May brush teeth frequently.
</bulimia-nervosa>

<anorexia-nervosa>
Restricting eating to maintain a percieved proper weight. 
Usually underweight. 
Intense fear of gaining weight. 
Multiple measurements of weight daily. 
Don't allow food to touch teeth.
Counting bites
Usually refuse to acknowledge the problem.
</anorexia-nervosa>

<radiation-therapy>
Consipation is a common side effecet if abdomen is irradiated.
Alopecia is expected if head is irradiated.
Fatige is a common and expected side effect.
Rash could occur and must be treated. 
Could result in difficulty in swollowing due to inflammation and thus require further intervention. 
</radiation-therapy>

<vomiting>
In complicated clients, elevate head of bed, suction the mouth, check lung sounds, and notify provider.
</vomiting>

<lumbar-puncture>
Hydrate well before the procedure. 
Instruct to void.
Either sit on the side of the bed while leaning forward or tuck knees to chest and lay on side.
Local anesthetic is injected. 
Spinal needle is inserted into subarachnoid space. 
Pressure in the space is measured then CSF is withdrawn. 
Client may feel some pressure and brief sharp pain with tingling down one or both legs. 
</lumbar-puncture>

<suctioning>
Hyperoxygenate for 30 seconds, suction for 5-10 seconds at a time. 
</suctioning>

<biot-respirations>
Seen in patients with brain damage. A cycle of rapid respirations followed by short period of apnea. 
</biot-respirations>

<cheyne-stokes-respirations>
Seen in patients with heart problems. A cycle that alternates between fast deep breaths with slow shallow respirations. 
</cheyne-stokes-respirations>

<stridor>
Occurs during inspiration. 
</stridor>

<wheezing>
Mostly during expiration but could also occur during inspiration. 
</wheezing>

<metoclopromide>
Stimulates the motility of upper GI tract and decreases nausea. 
</metoclopromide>

<cardio-pulmonary-resucitation>
First do chest compressions then open the airway after 30 compressions. 
</cardio-pulmonary-resucitation>

<urine-output>
Normal is 33-84ml/hour or 800 - 2000 ml / day   
</urine-output>

<diabetes-insipidus>
Could be caused by deteriorating head trauma from the pressure on the pituitary gland. 
</diabetes-insipidus>

</review>


