<?xml version="1.0" ?>

<empty>

	<heparin>
		PTT control is 38 seconds, theraputic should be 1.5 - 2.5 x control
Petechia on chest is an adverse effect
	</heparin>

	<phlebitis>
		Discontinue infusion and apply a warm soak, document
No need to contact the prescriber
	</phlebitis>

	<transfusion>
		Blood should be transfused within 2-4 hours
Needle guage should be 18-20G to insure that cells aren't damaged
Monitor clients for first 15 min then periodically after
	</transfusion>

	<urine>
		Normal out put is 800 to 2000 mL/day ()
	</urine>

	<benzodiazepines>
		Don't ambulate clients after administering a benzo, even to the bathroom
Don't administer an opiod after, due to risk of respiratory depression
	</benzodiazepines>

	<preoperative>
		teaching about the procedure and experience, taching about pain and pain relief, controling client's anxiety, basic needs like elimination are met, maintain NPO status
Alert the anesthesiologist of any PO meds given prior
	</preoperative>

	<parkinson>
		Early symptoms: fatigue, loss of smell
	</parkinson>

	<influenza>
		FDA approved antivirals: peramivir, zanamivir, oseltamivir, baloxavir
Antivirals decrease the efficacy of the vaccine
	</influenza>

	<glasgow-coma-scale>
		Assesses three areas of conciousness - verbal response, motor response, eye opening
Maximum score is 15, minimal score is 3
Eyes open (1-4): none, to pain, to speech, spontaneously
Verbal (1-5): none, incomprehensible, inappropriate, confused, oriented
Motor (1-6): none, abnormal extension, abnormal flexion, withdrawl, localizes pain, obeys commands
	</glasgow-coma-scale>

	<bladder-distension>
		Dull percussion over symphisis pubis
	</bladder-distension>

	<low-molecular-weight-heparin>
		aPTT is not used to monitor them, no frequent blood tests are required
Given to prevent lower limb blood clots
Lower risk of bleeding than heparin, but the risk is still present
	</low-molecular-weight-heparin>

	<LPN-duties>
		All clients must be stable and require ruoutine, unchaning procedures, they cannot care for clients who require assessments 
Colostomy care
Administering oral meds
	</LPN-duties>

	<potassium>
		Low - flattened T waves, prominent U waves, ST-segment depression, prolonged PR interval,
	</potassium>

	<para-thyroid-hormone>
		Primary target is the kidney and bone
Causes blood levels of calcium to rise 
Causes calcium conservation in the kidney
	</para-thyroid-hormone>

	<calcium>
		Bound with fatty acids
	</calcium>

	<nsaid>
		Increase blood pressure, counterindicated in individuals with hypertension
Affect platelet clotting, increase the risk of bleeding especially with
	</nsaid>

	<cholelithiasis>
		Risk factors include Native American and Hispanic origins, obesity, multiparousness, age over 40, fasting
	</cholelithiasis>

	<statin>
		Must be given at night when cholesterol production is highest
	</statin>

	<who-do-you-see-first-rules>
		Is the client stable or unstable? Eliminate stable clients.
Is the client experiencing expected or unexpeced findings? Eliminate expecting findgins. 
Are the reminaing answers referring to airway, breathing or circulation (ABCs)? Eliminate each non-priority answer option using the ABCs.
Are the reminaing asnwer options real (actual) or potential problems? Eliminate the potential problem answer options.
	</who-do-you-see-first-rules>

	<systemic-lupus-erythematosus>
		Malar rash - rash extending across the nasal bridge and upper cheeks.
	</systemic-lupus-erythematosus>

	<right-sided-heart-failure>
		Congestion of the gastric veins, resulting in anorexia and eventual development of ascites
	</right-sided-heart-failure>

	<lithium-toxicity>
		Early signs: nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, tremors and twitching. 
Late signs: fever, ataxia, confusion, and seizures.
	</lithium-toxicity>

	<fluid-intake>
		Normal fluid intake should be between 1,500 - 2,000 ml/day
	</fluid-intake>

	<skin-grafting>
		Priority should be given to grafit immobilization, since the graft must adhere to the site for vascularization to take place. It takes between 7-10 days to adhere.
	</skin-grafting>

	<low-hemoglobin>
		First apply oxygen to make sure the available hemoglobin is well oxygenated, place on cariac monitor, start the intravenous catheter, draw the blood work.
	</low-hemoglobin>

	<cushing-disease>
		Overproduction of corticosteroids, mainly cortisol or hypercortisolism. 
Cortisol is associated with an incrase in glucose levels, increased sodium levels, decreased potassium and calcium levels.
	</cushing-disease>

	<acidosis>
		Associated with hyperkalemia
	</acidosis>

	<fetal-kick-counting>
		Must be done the same time each day, preferrably after a meal in the left side lying position.
Should not be less then 10 kicks in 2 hours, or less then 3 kickins in one hour.
If the test fails, then a non-stress test should be performed.
	</fetal-kick-counting>

	<above-knee-amputation>
		Compression dressing should be maintained to minimize edema, prevent infection and shape the stubb. 
Elevate the amputated limb for 24 hours after surgery. 
Range of motion excercises every 2-4 hours.
No sitting in chair for prolonged times to prevent hip flexion contractions.
	</above-knee-amputation>

	<milieu-therapy>
		Intended to treat behaviour and personality disorders. All aspects of the environemnt are utilized to alter the behaviour and personality. Each member is assigned a set of responsibilities and activities that allow them to develop healthy social behaviours. 
Keys to successful therapy: support, structure, repetition, consistent expectations.
	</milieu-therapy>

	<myxedema>
		Refers to severe hypothyroidisim.
Symptoms: very cold, tired and sluggish.
	</myxedema>

	<poisoning>
		Call Poison Control Center not 911
	</poisoning>

	<uterine-hyper-tonicity>
		When one contractions lasts 2 minutes or longer or when there are 5 or more contractions in 10 minutes.
	</uterine-hyper-tonicity>

	<toilet-training>
		Ready between 18 months to 3 years
Parents must have 2 weeks of free time off work.
Child must be able to sit for 5-10 minutes.
Must be able to have fine motor skills to dress and unrdress.
	</toilet-training>

	<pediatric-cardiac-defect>
		Check child for hypoxia which is indicated by squatting after activity, cyanosis, tachycardia and sweating.
	</pediatric-cardiac-defect>

	<chronic-alcohol-abuse>
		Hypomagnesemia - trermors, confusion, racing heart - could be dangerous is severe.
	</chronic-alcohol-abuse>

	<deep-vein-thrombosis>
		Do not massage, promote bed rest and not moving the extremity, elevate the extremity on pillows to reduce edema and promote venous return.
	</deep-vein-thrombosis>

	<IV-Push>
		Port nearest to the insertion site.
Tubing above should be clamped.
Use a watch with to time push duration
	</IV-Push>

	<gastrostomy-tube>
		Monitor prealbumin levels, it has shorter half life than albumin and is a better reflection of the patient's nutritional status.
	</gastrostomy-tube>

	<poly-cystic-ovarian-syndrome>
		Metabolic disorder diagnosed in adolescence. Characterized by ovulatory dysfunction, amenorrhea, cysts in the ovaries, hyperandrogenism.
Most common in women under 30 and may cause infertility. 
Hormonal changes include increased testosterone, decreased progesterone and increased insulin resistance. 
Causes moood instability, stubborn weight gain, hair growth on face (hirsutism), acne. 
Women must strive to maintain normal weight, which can result in a more regular menstrual cycle.
	</poly-cystic-ovarian-syndrome>

	<leadership-models>
		Transformational leader - communicate their vision in a manner that is meaningful and exciting, insipires commitment from others and encourages self-motivation
Autocratic leader - (ruler with absolute power) leader makes decision with no input from staff.
Laissez faire leader - (french for let it be) leader does not want to make decisions but lets other decide.
Democratic leader - leader seeks inputs from staff before making decisions, primarly concernec with human relations and teamwork.
	</leadership-models>

	<bromocriptine>
		Dopamine receptor agonist.
Reduces prolacting levels (treats hyperprolactinemia).
Treats acromegaly by decreasing the amounts of human growth hormone.
Treats Parkinson's disease.
	</bromocriptine>

	<sequential-compression-devices>
		Remove at least once every 8 hours.
Monitor for one full cycle after applying.
	</sequential-compression-devices>

	<iron-supplements>
		Should be taken on empty stomach, with vitamin C enriched juice.
	</iron-supplements>

	<sulfonyureas>
		Developed in 1950's.
Increase the release of insulin from the pancreas.
Common meds in class:
glyburide, glimepiride, glipizide
Common interactions: beta blockers - mask hypoglycemia which is the primary adverse effect of oral antidiabetic agents.
Gemfibrozil - cholesterol medication, could increase the hypoglycemic effects of sulfonyureas.
Aspirin and oral anticoagulants, MAOIs, sulfonamides (antibiotics mostly for UTI), cimetidine  - displace the sulfonyureas from the transport proteins, thereby increasing their effect
Thiazides, Isoniazid, Phenytoin, Corticosteroids - decrease the effects of sulfonyureas.
	</sulfonyureas>

	<ginkgo-biloba>
		Can cause bleeding, taking it with other meds that cause bleeding can increase the effect. 
Thought to increase mental fitness. Studies failed to show any increase except in dimentia.
	</ginkgo-biloba>

	<ginseng>
		Increases the hypoglycemic effects of sulfonyureas.
Boost energy, lowers blood sugar and cholesterol, reduces stress, manages sexual dysfunction.
	</ginseng>

	<lumbar-puncture>
		Food and fluids are not restricted
After procedure instruct the client to lay flat for 6-8 hours
Encourage fluids
	</lumbar-puncture>

	<cancer>
		Most common cancer deaths are from smoking associated lung cancer. 
Most common cancer diagnosis is from skin cancer.
	</cancer>

	<basal-skull-fracture>
		CNS leak from the ear
	</basal-skull-fracture>

	<suicide>
		Ask about frequency, duration and intensity of suicidal thoughts (suicidal ideation).
Ask abou the suicide plan like the method and time and place.
Ask about prior attempts or rehersals. 
Evaluate the intent to follow through with the plan. 
Maintain a safe environment and place on constant observation.
	</suicide>

	<influenza-vaccine>
		Fever is common and expected side effect, up to 39C (102.8F)
	</influenza-vaccine>

	<shock>
		Hypovolemic, cardiogenic, obstructive, distributive (neurogenic, septic, anaphylectic).
Signs and symptoms: tachycardia, low blood pressure, palor.
	</shock>

	<hyperthyroidism>
		Tachycardia, intolerance to heat, polyphagia (excessive eating), nervousness and dry hair as well as hypertension.
	</hyperthyroidism>

	<vena-cava-syndrome>
		Aka: supine hypotensive syndrome
Reduction of cardiac output when the gravid uterus puts pressure on the vena cava, especially in the supine position.
Lying on the side, takes the pressure off the vena cava.
	</vena-cava-syndrome>

	<retinal-detachment>
		Medical emergency.
Feels like a curtain is being pulled over eyes.
	</retinal-detachment>

	<play-by-age>
		Infant (0-1) - solitary play, focusted on their own activity but enjoy the presence of others.
Toddler (1-3) - parallel play, playing along side but not with others.
	</play-by-age>

	<tricuspid-valve>
		Auscultate at S1: 5th intercostal, left sternal border.
	</tricuspid-valve>

	<nebulizer>
		Delivers medication through water mist. 
Excessive use can cause hypervolemia due to excessive fluid absorption.
	</nebulizer>

	<methycillin-resistant-staphylococcus-aureus>
		Contact precautions.
	</methycillin-resistant-staphylococcus-aureus>

	<neisseria-meningitidis>
		Droplet precautions.
	</neisseria-meningitidis>

	<mycobacterium-tuberculosis>
		Airborne precautions.
	</mycobacterium-tuberculosis>

	<mean-arterial-pressure>
		Should be at least 65.
MAP = (S+2D)/3; where S is the systolic pressure and D is the diastollic pressure.
	</mean-arterial-pressure>

	<hypotension>
		Begin fluid resuscitation with crystalloid solution of at least 30ml/kg over 30 min. 
If fluids don't work begin norepinephrine (Levophed) or dopamine.
	</hypotension>

	<extravasation>
		Happen when caustic IV solution leaks outside of the blood vessel and irritates the tissue. 
Symptoms include pain, burning and edema around the IV site.
	</extravasation>

	<infiltration>
		Happens when non caustic IV solution leaks outside of the blood vessel.
	</infiltration>

	<skin-patch>
		Heat greatly increases medicine absoprtion and could result in an overdose.
	</skin-patch>

	<aminophylline>
		Interacts with propranolol, decreasing the bodies ability to metaboloize it leading to toxicity.
	</aminophylline>

	<monoamine-oxidase-inhibitors>
		Avoid tyramine
Common medications in this class: isocarboxazid.
	</monoamine-oxidase-inhibitors>

	<renal-calculi>
		To prevent, ingest between 2,500 - 3,000 mL of fluid per day.
	</renal-calculi>

	<magnetic-resonsnace-imaging>
		Presence of anyurism clips is contraindicated as they could be made from a ferromagnetic material.
	</magnetic-resonsnace-imaging>

	<brachytherapy>
		Surgical placement of irradiated beads near the tumor. 
All treatments should be clustered together as to not come into the patient's room too many times. 
Pregnant women and children should avoid contact with the patient.
Other visitors are allowed after 24 post insertion, visits must be limited to 30 min.
	</brachytherapy>

	<walker>
		Lift the walker, don't slide it, 8-10 inches ahead.
	</walker>

	<cardiac-temponade>
		
	</cardiac-temponade>

	<trigeminal-nerve>
		Sensation of touch on face
Controlling muscles needed to chew
	</trigeminal-nerve>

	<cessarian-section>
		Legs could be numb from local anesthetic, which is a normal finding.
	</cessarian-section>

	<myasthenia-gravis>
		Corticosteroids are often a part of the treatment schedule.
	</myasthenia-gravis>

	<incident-report>
		Should be completed when the staff or clients are subject to danger, such as wrong medication, complications from procedures like extravasation, breask in asceptic technique, client refuses treatment, client voices dissatisfaction with care that cannot be resolved. 
Does not go into the client record, used for management purposes.
	</incident-report>

	<suicide-assessment>
		Intent to Die - how serious a patient is in carrying through
Severity of ideation - how persistent are the thoughts
Degree of planning
	</suicide-assessment>

	<cephalohematoma>
		Does not cross suture lines
	</cephalohematoma>

	<systemic-inflammatory-response-syndrome>
		Caused by mechanical tissue trauma and tissue ischemia, could lead to multi organ Failure
Release of inflammatory markers, activation of coagulation cascade, decreased perfusion and hypotension
	</systemic-inflammatory-response-syndrome>

	<anorexia-nervosa>
		Refusal to eat for the fear of gaining weight
Increased BUN due to lower blood volume (hyperuricemia)
	</anorexia-nervosa>

	<disease-prevention>
		primary - preventing the disease
secondary - early detection
teriary - limit disease progression
	</disease-prevention>

	<retroperitoneal-bleeding>
		Discoloration around the umbilicus (Cullen's sign) or flank (Grey Turner's sign)
Abdominal pain or numbness of lower extremities (due to spinal nerve compression
Volume replacement is the priority using colloid or crystalloid solutions
	</retroperitoneal-bleeding>

	<vasopressin>
		Should replace fluid first before adminstration of vasopressin
	</vasopressin>

	<tension-pneumothorax>
		Tracheal deviation
Hypotension
	</tension-pneumothorax>

	<glomerulonephritis>
		Causes an elevated serum anti-streptolysin o (ASO) titer
	</glomerulonephritis>

	<psoriasis>
		Presents as white, silvery, scaly patches on the skin 
Most common areas are elbows, knees, scalp and scrotum
	</psoriasis>

	<radiation-safety>
		Visitation no more than 30min
Distance no less than 6 feet
No pregnant staff or visitors
	</radiation-safety>

	<myelomeningocele>
		Cover with moist dressing
Take great care to avoid rupture, as CNS infection would be imminent 
Surgery done 24-48 hours after birth
	</myelomeningocele>

	<gun-safety>
		Store ammunition separately from guns
Guns should never be stored loaded
	</gun-safety>

	<deep-tendon-reflexes>
		Rated on a 4 point scale 
0 - no response
1 - slight, but definitive response
2 - brisk; normal
3 - very brisk
4 - overactive - abnormal
	</deep-tendon-reflexes>

	<magnesium>
		Acts as a smooth muscle relaxer, resulsts in vasodialtion and reduced blood pressure
Normal levels 1.3 - 2.1 mEq/L
	</magnesium>

	<aldosterone>
		Main mineralcorticoid produced by the zona glomerulosa of the adrenal gland
Essential for sodium conservation
	</aldosterone>

	<epipen>
		Inject into the vastus lateralis muscle
	</epipen>

	<oral-contraceptives>
		Suppress the production of breastmilk, if the client is breastfeeind other methods of contraception should be used.
	</oral-contraceptives>

	<intra-ocular-pressure>
		Normal is 21 or below
	</intra-ocular-pressure>

	<glaucoma>
		If the pressure readings are borderline, pressure should be take at multiple points throughout the day.
Secondary glaucoma could be caused by neurovasuclar disorders, such as CVAs.
Vision loss occurs in peripheral vision initially.
Open-Angle - affects both eyes simultaneously, slow progression
Closed-Angle - usually affects one eye at a time. 
More common in black race - six fold incrase
Other risk factors include being higly far sighted.
	</glaucoma>

	<fall>
		Complete a physical assessment of the client to make sure they didn't sustain any injuries, if they didn't: fill out an incident report then call the provider, then call the family.
	</fall>

	<T4>
		Normal T4 levels are 5.0 - 12.0 microgram/dL
	</T4>

	<leukocytes>
		Normal levels are between 4.5 -11k units per microliter.
	</leukocytes>

	<dementia>
		Common to self isolate while eating.
	</dementia>

	<tuberculin-skin-test>
		Administration of a live-virus-vaccine may cause a false negative on a TST.
If administering a live virus vaccine it should be done on the same day as the TST or waiting 4-6 weeks after a live vaccine. 
False negative could also occur due to a weakened immune system.
Bacille Calmette-Guerin (vaccine) could give a false positive if given within 4-6 weeks of TST.
	</tuberculin-skin-test>

	<acquired-immondeficinecy-syndrome>
		Could produce a false negative on a tuberculin-skin-test due to immune system supresssion.
	</acquired-immondeficinecy-syndrome>

	<dysphagia>
		Level 1 - pureed foods, need no chewing.
Level 2 - mechanically altered foods, moist foods that needs some chewing. Examples are meatloaf with mash and gravy. Meats should be ground and gavies are used to soften. 
Level 3 - advanced diet, soft solid foods need more chewing. Example would be pasta, thinly sliced chicken. Exclude foods that are tough, cruncy or sticky.
Level 4 - general diet, all foods included.
	</dysphagia>

	<diabetes-insipidus>
		Characterized by a decrease in anti-diuretic-hormone.
Causes increased urine output and increased sodium concentrations.
Excretion of dilute urine at 200 ml/hr +
	</diabetes-insipidus>

	<urine-specific-gravity>
		Normal range is 1.010 - 1.030
	</urine-specific-gravity>

	<access-port>
		Should be scrubbed for 30-60 seconds prior to use.
	</access-port>

	<abuse>
		Risk factors for older adults: female, reduced social interaction, at least one physical or mental impairment.
	</abuse>

	<fetal-heart-rate>
		Should be heard with a doppler at 10-12 weeks.
	</fetal-heart-rate>

	<ballotment>
		Movement of the fetus that is palpated with a tap on the uterus.
Should be first felt at 4-5 months.
	</ballotment>

	<aminoglycosides>
		Example: gentamycin
Side effects: ototoxicity, nephgrotoxicity.
	</aminoglycosides>

	<gentamycin>
		An aminoglycoside antibiotics.
Treats infections caused by pseudomonas aeruginosa, Escherichia-coli and staphylococcus.
	</gentamycin>

	<dipstick-urinalisys>
		Tests for: specific gravity, pH, protein, leukocytes, blood, ketones, glucose
	</dipstick-urinalisys>

	<straight-catherterization>
		In home setting: no need for sterile procedures, catheters are reused after washing them with anti-bacterial soap and povidone-iodine.
	</straight-catherterization>

	<macular-degeneration>
		After surgery the client has to remain face down.
	</macular-degeneration>

	<Jackson-Pratt-drain>
		To remove: release the suction, remove sutures, ask patient to breath deeply and regularly, pull drain out in one motion, assess the exit site and cover it with gauze.
	</Jackson-Pratt-drain>

	<continuous-renal-replacement-therapy>
		Indications: patients who have cardiovascular impartments that can't tolerate low BP that accompanies hemodialysis.
Slow continuous filtering of the blood.
Does not require a av fistula, blood is drawn from femoral or subcalvian vein. 
Hemofilter should be changed every 24-48 hours
Clients are prone to hypothermia
	</continuous-renal-replacement-therapy>

	<isoniazid>
		Could induce hepatitis/liver-failure.
	</isoniazid>

	<Jaundice>
		Best places to assesss for jaundice are abdomen skin, sclera of the eyes and hard pallete.
In Asian-American populations, skin may have a natural yellow tone so the best place to assess for jaundice in this populace is the hard pallete.
	</Jaundice>

	<LPN-delegation>
		Stable clients.
Cannot delegate teaching or tasks that require assessment.
	</LPN-delegation>

	<syndrome-of-inappropriate-antidiuretic-hormone-secretion>
		Causes the body to retain too much water.
Dilutional hyponatremia occurs.
Hypervolemia causes tachycardia.
Treatment includes restricting fluid intake to 500-600ml/24h, diuretics, daily weights and strict intake and output.
End result is seizures and brain swelling.
	</syndrome-of-inappropriate-antidiuretic-hormone-secretion>

	<newborn-facial-paralysis>
		Occurs because of compression of cranial nerve VII, usually resolves in a few days to 3 weeks, or could be permanent.
	</newborn-facial-paralysis>

	<neonatal-red-reflex>
		Should be present in both eyes and should be symmetrical. 
If not present or not symmetrical it is considered an opthalmic emergency.
Absense could cause blindness if not treated right away.
	</neonatal-red-reflex>

	<constipation>
		Drink warm fluids they promote peristalsis and provide a mild cathartic effect, take a warm shower which helps promote abdominal muscle relaxation
	</constipation>

	<dehydration>
		Drink a solution high in sodium and potassium.
	</dehydration>

	<cyanosis>
		In dark skinned clinets assesed on light skin areas such as the soles of feet and palms of hands, oral cavity membranes and conjunctiva with bluish or light gray color.
	</cyanosis>

	<post-traumatic-stress-disorder>
		Tendancy for violence and suicide. 
Allow talk of traumatic event.
Teach about conditioning.
Remove weapons from space.
	</post-traumatic-stress-disorder>

	<diphenhydramine>
		Has anticholinergic properties.
Contraindicated in closed angle glaucoma, small bowel obstruction - may increase obstruction, and peptic ulcers as it may increase bleeding.
	</diphenhydramine>

	<status-epilepticus>
		Tonic-clonic (tonic - extension of arms/legs, clonic - contraction of arms and legs) should not last more than 60-90 seconds. Seizure followed by small rest then followed by another sezure or a seizure that lasts more than 5 minutes
is called status epilepticus. 
Benzodiazapeines like diazapam are presricbed as they increase the seizure threshold in the brain. Given IV push, rectally or nasaly.
	</status-epilepticus>

	<seizure>
		Lay on side so saliva can drain. Give oxygen if there are color changes. Lower clinet to floor, protect the head, clear objects from area. Administer Lore/diazepam. Stay with the client until alert.
	</seizure>

	<Hodgekin-lymphoma>
		Painless swelling of cervical lymph node, usually single. The lymph node is usually freely movable, firm and painless.
Ingestion of alcohol may result in the pain of the diseased lymph node.
	</Hodgekin-lymphoma>

	<post-anasthesia-care-unit>
		Priority is to maintain ABCs upon reiceval, second priority to to monitor the incision site, third is giving presribed meds.
	</post-anasthesia-care-unit>

	<tardive-dyskinesia>
		Characterized by abnormal facial or tongue movements. Treated by decreasing or discontinuing antipsychotic medication. Symptoms may reverse however may be permanent as well.
	</tardive-dyskinesia>

	<pseudoparkinsonism>
		Symptoms that mimic Parkinson's syndrome such as shuffling gait, tremors and rigidity. Treated with anticholinergics.
	</pseudoparkinsonism>

	<acute-dystonic-reaction>
		Caused by too much cholinergic neurotransmitters compared to dopaminergic ones. Contraction of facial and neck muscles, treated with diphenhydramine or benzotropine. Symtpoms improve after 10-30 min after administering IV anticholinergics.
	</acute-dystonic-reaction>

	<dantrolene>
		Used for muscle spasms, and it coudld be used for malignant hypothermia.
	</dantrolene>

	<infant>
		Ages below 1 year.
Erikson - Trust vs Mistrust
	</infant>

	<toddler>
		Ages 1 - 3
Erikson - Autonomy vs Shame and Doubt
Speaks in sdgments of 3-4 words.
Able to express likes and dislikes. 
Assertion of independence
Understand cuasality.

Encourage parents: postive reinforcement, give simple rationals, provide two selections for choice
Communication: 
12months - gestures (pointing, waving), follows one step commands, single words.
24 months - repeats words and phrases (echolalia), combines 2-3 words together, impulsive (tantrums), vocabulary of 40-50 words.
36 months - multiple words into pharases, verbalizes name, age and gender. Short conversations, follow 3 step commands, vocabulary of 200-1000 words.
	</toddler>

	<pre-schooler>
		Ages 3 - 5
Erikson - Initiative vs Guilt
Uses complete sentences. 
Could perform simple chores like putting away toys, or gringing items to the table.
Understands right from wrong.
	</pre-schooler>

	<school-age>
		Age 5-13
Erikson - Industry vs. Inferiority
	</school-age>

	<teenager>
		Ages 13-21
Erikson - Identity vs Role Confusion
	</teenager>

	<young-adult>
		Ages 21-39
Erikson - Intimacy vs Isolation.
	</young-adult>

	<middle-aged-adult>
		Ages 40-65
Erikson - Generativty vs Stagnation
	</middle-aged-adult>

	<older-adult>
		Ages 65+
Erikson - Integrity vs Despair
	</older-adult>

	<detached-retina>
		Symptoms: floaters across field of vision, blurred vision, black curtain over visual field

Surgery: scleral buckling or laser photocoagulation

Post operatively:
Limit eye movement of both eyes (even with sureger on one eye), bed rest with eye patch over operated eye.
May require special positioning to maintain intravitreal bubble. 
Give eye drops - antibiotics, antiinflammatory and dilating agenets.
	</detached-retina>

	<lactulose>
		Traps and expells ammonia from the blood via the feces. Results in soft formed stools.
Also used as a laxative.
	</lactulose>

	<doppler-ultrasound>
		Probe held at 45 degrees.
Probe should be held lightly as to not obliterate the pulse. If movement is performed move distal to proximal.
Gel should be warm to reduce vasoconstriction.
	</doppler-ultrasound>

	<pulse-deficit>
		Difference between apical and peripheral pulses.
	</pulse-deficit>

	<thiazide-diuretics>
		Examples: Chlorothiazide, hydrochlorothiazide, indapamide, chlorthalidone, metolazone. 
Act directly on the kidney to inhibit the sodium/chloride cotransporter - which has a function of reabsorbing sodium and chloride ions in DCT.
Increase sodium secretion.
Increase potassium secretion.
Decrease calcium secretion, thereby increasing serum calcium.
Promotes alkalosis by increasing the release of hydrogen through urine.
	</thiazide-diuretics>

	<histrionic-disorder>
		Overreaction to events.
	</histrionic-disorder>

	<electro-convulsive-therapy>
		Good candidate: pregnant, suicidal or catatonic, major depression, bipolar mania and schitzophrenia. 
Contraindications: cardiac problems, osteoporosis, loose teeth. 
2-3 tretments per week for a month or 6-12 sessions total
Performed under anesthesia
	</electro-convulsive-therapy>

	<central-line-associated-bloodstream-infection>
		In order to get accurate cultures, first collect blood cultures from two separate peripheral sites then begin empiric antibiotic therapy with broad spectrum AB right away without waiting for cultures to return.
	</central-line-associated-bloodstream-infection>

	<non-tunneled-central-venous-access-device>
		Used for a short term, in acute care settings.
Insertion procedure:
Full sterile field with gowns, caps and masks and patient is covered with full body sterile drapes. 
Patient is placed in Trandelenburg position (head down) to contain air emboli in lower chambers and to produce dilation of neck and subclavian veins. 
Subclavian vein is used most of the time. Sometimes basilic, cephalic or as a last resort femoral veins could be used.
Area is swabbed with chlorhexidine to remove any residual oils. 
Patient is asked to turn head away from insertion site to give more tension. 
Lidocaine is injected into tissue to numb the area.
Large bore needle is insertered parallel to the clavicle and guided deeper until it hits the vein.
Patient is asked to take a deep breath and perform the Valsalva manuver, that is bear down, to create a positive pressure phase in central venous pressure and make it harder for air emboli to move in, as the cather is guided through the needle and into the superior vena cava. 
Needle is removed and catheter is sutured to the skin.
Chlorhexidine impregnated gauze with transparent dressing is placed over the insertion site.
Catheter placement is confirmed with an x-ray (as well as to rule out accidental puncture of the pleura and pneumothorax)
	</non-tunneled-central-venous-access-device>

	<glucocorticoids>
		Increase in times of stress.
	</glucocorticoids>

	<Addisonian-crisis>
		Due to rapid withdrawl of corticosteroid medication, or stress factors.
Symptoms: hypotension, tachycardia, electrolyte imbalances.
Can lead to shock and circulatory collapse.
	</Addisonian-crisis>

	<adrenal-gland>
		Zona glomerulose - mineralcorticoid - aldosterone
Zona fasciculada - glucocorticoids - cortisol
Zona reticularis - androgens
Medulla - catecholamines - epinephrine and norepinephrine
	</adrenal-gland>

	<lactation>
		Need to add 400-500 cal daily to pre-pregnancy caloric intake to compensate for breasfeeding.
	</lactation>

	<Paget-disease>
		Interferes with bone remodeling, causes enlarged skull, curving of leg bones, bones become weaker.
Elevated serum alkaline phosphatase (ALP).
Treated with same medications as osteoporosis (biphosphonates).
	</Paget-disease>

	<overdose>
		Check for responsiveness and breathing rate - if none begin CPR
Call for nearby helps
Have someone call 911
Have someone get AED 
Have someone get nalaxone
	</overdose>

	<GTPAL>
		Gravida - number of pregnancies (twins or more count as one)
Term - number of deliveries of 38 weeks + (twins or more count as one)
Preterm - number of deliveries 20 - 37 weeks (twins or more count as one)
Abortions - number of pregnancies ending prior to 20 weeks (including spontaneously) (twins or more count as 1)
Living - number of living children
	</GTPAL>

	<gravida-parity>
		Only uses two numbers
Gravida - number of pregnancies (twins or more count as one)
Parity - number of pregnancies carried past 20 weeks, including pregncies that eneded in spontaneous abortion. (Also counts multiple embryos as one)
	</gravida-parity>

	<intestinal-secretions>
		Hihgh in bicarbonate, loss of which (like in iliostomys) leads to metabolic acidosis
	</intestinal-secretions>

	<metabolic-acidosis>
		Associated with hyperkalemia, Kussmaul respirations (deep rapid breathing to rid body of CO2) and tachycardia.
	</metabolic-acidosis>

	<eating-disorders>
		Observe the client before, during and after meals.
Avoid discussions about food especially while eating.
Require food consumption within limited amount of time.
Feed through an NG tube if required.
	</eating-disorders>

	<Haemophilus-influenzae>
		Leading cause of bacterial meningitis in children under 5 years old. Could also cause pneumonia, sepsis and death.
	</Haemophilus-influenzae>

	<delivery-instructions>
		Panting through the mouth helps prevent immediate delivery. Confirm that the neonate doesn't have a cord around the neck before proceeding with delivery. If cord is detected slip two fingers between it and the neonate to give space for breathing and continue with delivery.
	</delivery-instructions>

	<cervix-dilation>
		5cm/hour in nulliparous women
10cm/hour in multiparous women
	</cervix-dilation>

	<actinic-keratosis>
		Small papule with rough, dry, scaly skin.
	</actinic-keratosis>

	<ciprofloxacin>
		Class of drugs known as fluoroquinolones.
Milk, yougurt and ceffeine interferes with medication absorption, avoid taking together with the medicine. Could be consumed in between doses though.
Calcium could alter absorption and should not be taken within 6 hours of the medication. 
Could be taken with or without meals.
Increase in fluid intake is required to prevent crystalluria and renal calculi, cipro increases the risk for both. 
May cause increased sensitivity to sun.
	</ciprofloxacin>

	<meconium>
		Usually passed within 24 hours.
	</meconium>

	<false-labor>
		Contractions are irregular and don't get closer together.
Don't start from the back and radiate through the abdomen, unlike in true labor. Usually the pain is only felt in the front.
Contractions stop with relaxation.
	</false-labor>

	<chemical-stress-test>
		Medications most commonly used: 
Dipyridamole thallium 201
Adenosine
Dobutamine
IV medications given to clients to simulate a stress test on the heart when client is unable to do physical activity.
A sonogram is performed to detect any abnormalities.
	</chemical-stress-test>

	<mixing-insulin>
		Done to avoid giving the patient multiple injections if they require both short term and extended action insulin injections.
Most commonly mixed insulins are regular and NPH (Neutral Protamine Hagedorn)
Never mix insulin Glargine (Lantus) with any other insulin.
Administer the injection within 5-10 min after drawing it up because regular insulin binds to NPH and decreases the action (of regular insulin).
Why does the order matter: NPH insulin should not be introduced into regular insulin vial because of the binding effect.
	</mixing-insulin>

	<end-of-life>
		Clients often times refuse fluids in last days, effects of dehydration take a toll on the mind.
Clients could experience restlessness, agitation and hallucinations.
	</end-of-life>

	<effects-of-aging>
		Decreased pain tolerance.
	</effects-of-aging>

	<nutrition-fat>
		Saturated and trans: solid at room temperature, found in animal tallow
Places: butter, pork, chicken and beef fat, cakes, nuts, chips, tropical plant oils (coconut, palm etc.), margerine
	</nutrition-fat>

	<adult-diaper>
		To ensure proper fit front absorbent matt should come to the naval
Change diaper after 20 ounces of absorbency is reached or after 2 wettings, usually 2-3 times per day.
Avoid wearing a large diaper to avoid frequent changes.
Use a barrier cream such as zinc oxide after each diaper change.
	</adult-diaper>

	<neurogenic-shock>
		Loss of sympathetic tone. 
Most common cuase is damage to the spinal column above T6 
Symptoms are dry, warm skin, low bp and maybe brady cardia.
	</neurogenic-shock>

	<games-by-age>
		Toddler (1.5-3) - picture books, pounding board, regular household items, manu opportunities for exploration, 4 - 12 piece wood puzzles, blocks, cars, crayons, large paintbrush, dolls, balls, push-pull toys, rocking horses.
Pre-Schooler (3-5) - dress up clothes, tricycle, skates.
	</games-by-age>

	<why-questions>
		Don't ask why questions - they are confrontational.
	</why-questions>

	<Guillain-Barre-Syndrome>
		Ascending paralysis that starts with tingling in feet and could paralyze the body, including breathing and swallowing.
Could be triggered by a viral or a bacterial infection.
Autoimmune condition which affects the myelination of the nerves.
Treatments could include plasma exchange and immunoglobulin therapy.
Has no effect on cognitive function.
Recovery happens in 90% of cases but usually takes several months to a few years.
	</Guillain-Barre-Syndrome>

	<central-venous-access>
		Femoral site has a higher chance for infection, femoral site is only used if subclavian site is unavailble.
	</central-venous-access>

	<fundus-decension>
		Rate of 1cm per day, after 10 days should be below the pubic bone.
Subinvolution could cause hemorrhage.
	</fundus-decension>

	<lochia>
		Rubra - 1 to 4 days after birth, small blood clots not larger than plum are normal
Serosa - pink to brown discharge, 4-10 days after delivery
Alba - yellow whitish discharge from 10 - 14 days.
	</lochia>

	<postpartum-assessment>
		Massage boggy uterus. 
Monitor for thrombophlebitis in legs, ambulate.
	</postpartum-assessment>

	<brain-lobes>
		parietal - sensation and orientation in space
temporal - audio processing
occipital - visual
frontal - higher order fuctions, personality, speech, emotions.
	</brain-lobes>

	<dementia-bathing>
		Sing or talk continuously to help the client relaxation.
Expose only one area at a time to keep warm and provide privacy
Bathe slowly and explain every step.
	</dementia-bathing>

	<cardio-pulmonary-resucitation>
		Assess for responsiveness - make sure the patient is not sleeping or easily roused
Activate emergency response- shout to someone to call 911
Check the pulse as you scan for signs of life - if yes check breathing if no got to next step
Begin chest compressions
After 30 compressions open the airway and give two breaths
Resume compressions at rate of 30:2
	</cardio-pulmonary-resucitation>

	<libel>
		Writing false information about someone
	</libel>

	<prenatal-diagnostics>
		Glucose tolerance test
HIV test
Hep B test
Blood typing
STI test
	</prenatal-diagnostics>

	<maternal-serum-alpha-fetoprotein>
		Blood test given to the mother at 15-20 weeks (second trimester)
Assesses for neural tube defects (such as spina bifida or ananecephaly) and other chromosomal abnormalities.
	</maternal-serum-alpha-fetoprotein>

	<bone-marrow-biopsy>
		Using bones such as iliac crest or sternum
Could result in heavy bleeding due to deep penetration of tissue.
	</bone-marrow-biopsy>

	<anxiety>
		Anxiety is a normal response to stress.
Management of anxiety is geared with learning to cope with existing experiences, not seeking out new ones to &quot;conquer&quot; anxiety.
Calling the therapis every time there is some anxiety is not recommended since the patient might become too reliant on them.
	</anxiety>

	<furosemide>
		Potassium wasting diuretic.
	</furosemide>

	<spironolactone>
		Potassium sparing diuretic.
	</spironolactone>

	<phenozopyridine>
		Causes urine to become organge or red, which is normal.
If the kidneys cannot excrete it fast enough then the skin could become dislored too, in which case the med should be stopped immediately.
	</phenozopyridine>

	<post-partum>
		It's normal to urinate up to 3000ml per day for 2-3 days post, as fluid accumulated during pregnancy is leaving the body.
	</post-partum>

	<Naegeles-rule>
		Determine first day of last menstrual period
Subtract 3 calendar months from that time
Add 7 days
	</Naegeles-rule>

	<fundal-height>
		Increases by 1cm/week starting at 12-14 weeks and lasts until 36 weeks, then it varies.
Rises just above the pubis symphysis at about 12-14 weeks.
	</fundal-height>

	<pacemakers>
		Hearing aid may affect placement of the transmitter, as it shouldn't come within 6 inches of it.
Avoid placing devices that are battery operated or magnetic close to the transmitter.
Do not stay close near anti-theft devlices (like metal detecotrs) walk through them at a normal pace.
Avoid welding equipment, large generators, radar towers, and MRIs.
Usually place in upper left chest or under left clavicle. 
Electrical equipment that is grounded and well mantained is ok.
Common house appliances like microwaves, remotes, electric blankets will not affect the pacemaker.
	</pacemakers>

	<Dupuytrens-contracture>
		Thickening of skin near the base of the palm which causes fingers to contract towards the wrist or deflect.
Most often affects ring and pinky fingers.
Treatment includes surgery, using a needle to break the tissue and enzyme injections to soften the tissue.
Most commonly associated with middle age (50+) men of Scandinavian or Celtic descnet and is assaociated with diabetes, gout, arthritis and alcoholism.
	</Dupuytrens-contracture>

	<Duchenne-muscular-dystrophy>
		Genetic disorder characterizide by progressive muscle degeneration.
Typically found in boys.
Starts around ages 2-3, affects the legs first, affects the heart and breathing muscles later.
Life expectancy is around 16 to early 20s.
	</Duchenne-muscular-dystrophy>

	<packed-red-blood-cells>
		Administered with 18G catheter.
Should be administered in less than 4 hours to prevent bacterial contamination.
	</packed-red-blood-cells>

	<loop-diuretic>
		Examples: furosemide, bumetanide, torsemide
They are potassium wasting.
	</loop-diuretic>

	<interpersonal-behviour>
		Do not ask why questions, they are confrontational even before the facts are known.
Do involve emotional aspects into your questions as they are also confrontational.
	</interpersonal-behviour>

	<aspirin>
		Could be taken alongside clopidogrel.
	</aspirin>

	<blood-pressure>
		Optimal position for measuring BP is sitting upright. Laying down may incrase the reading by as much as 8 mmHg
	</blood-pressure>

	<multiple-sclerosis>
		Avoid overexposure to heat or cold - may damage areas that have lost sensation. May excerbate MS symptoms.
	</multiple-sclerosis>

	<urinalysis>
		The sample does not need to be sterile. 
If obtaining from a catheter, use sterile technique to not introduce infection into the catheter, but the sample itself doens't need to be sterile.
	</urinalysis>

	<ascites>
		Pushes on the lungs, decreasing lung capacity
	</ascites>

	<scabies>
		Transmission of scabies occurs through mites.
	</scabies>

	<sickle-cell-crisis>
		Blood test shows increased reticulocyte (immature red blood cells) count.
Hematocrit is decreased. 
Hemoglobin level is decreased. 
Causes: hypoxemia, dehydration, infection, excessive esercise, cold temperatures.
Treatment: oxygenation, hydration, adequate rest, warmth.
	</sickle-cell-crisis>

	<alcohol-withdrawal>
		Symptoms occur 4-6 hours after last drink and last up to 14 days.
Treatment is to use benzodiazepines to alleviate the agitation. 
Common benzodiazapeine to use is chlordiazepoxide. 
Symtpoms - tremor, insomnia, dilated pupils, tachycardia, perspiration, hallucinations.
	</alcohol-withdrawal>

	<opioid-withdrawl>
		shivering, abdominal cramping, muscle and bone pain, vomiting, diarrhea.
	</opioid-withdrawl>

	<ibuprofen>
		Increases the hypoglycemic effect of oral antidiabetics.
Increases risk of bleeding.
Increases risk of heart attack and stroke as early as a week after taking it consistently.
	</ibuprofen>

	<febrile-transfusion-reaction>
		Temperature increase &gt; 1 degree Celsius
Headache
Nausea/vomiting
	</febrile-transfusion-reaction>

	<hemolytic-transfusion-reaction>
		Symptoms: chills, low back/chest pain, hypotension, tachycardia
Treatment: stop the transfusion, obtain a urine specime, maintain blood volume and renal perfusion with an IV colloid solution (like albumin, gelatin, dextran, starch).
	</hemolytic-transfusion-reaction>

	<chronic-kidney-disease>
		Diet includes increased calories, animal protein (not plant), low potassium, low phosphorus and low sodium, limit dairy to 1 cup of milk or 1 ounce of cheese per day (because of phosphorus limits)
	</chronic-kidney-disease>

	<chronic-kidney-disease>
		Limit potassium and phosphorus.
	</chronic-kidney-disease>

	<chronic-kidney-disease>
		Diet needs to be low in protein, sodium, potassium and phosphorus.
	</chronic-kidney-disease>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Treatment is to administer insulin, insulin activates sodium-proton pump which pumps sodium ions in to the cell and hydrogen ions out, the influx of sodium activates the the sodium-potassium pump which job it's to maintain intracellular potassium concentrations higher and sodium concentrations lower. The Na-K pump exports 3 ions of sodium and imports two ions of potassium, lowering the overall serum potassium concentration.
Symptom is an elevated T wave
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hypocalcemia>
		tetany - spasms of hands, legs and feet, could also result in breating and cardio disturbances, overactive deep tendon reflexes, muscle twitching.
Chvostek sign - facial contraction when tapping on the facial nerve.
Trousseau sign - muscle scpasm of the hand and wrist when blood pressure cuff is applied.
Finger numbness.
	</hypocalcemia>

	<hyperthermia>
		Give acetaminophen and apply a cooling blanket.
	</hyperthermia>

	<hypocalcemia>
		Muscle cramps, Chvostek sign (facial nerve spasm), Trousseaue's sign (bp cuff dorsiflexion)
	</hypocalcemia>

	<hypercalcemia>
		Weakness, nausea, polyurea
	</hypercalcemia>

	<Hyperkalemia>
		Promotes reabsorption of hydrogen ions, leading to acidosis.
	</Hyperkalemia>

	<hypernatremia>
		Could be caused by diabetes-insipidus
	</hypernatremia>

	<Hypervolemia>
		Causes tachycardia.
	</Hypervolemia>

	<hypokalemia>
		Muscle weakness, especially in the legs. Parasthesia in the hands.
	</hypokalemia>

	<cushing-triad>
		Indicates increase in intracranial pressure. 
Bradycardia, irregular respirations, widened pulse pressure.
	</cushing-triad>

	<corticosteroid>
		Suppress the immune system and could give a false negative on tuberculin-skin-test.
	</corticosteroid>

	<liver-failure>
		Decrease fat in diet, incrase calories, increase carbs, decrease sodium, decrease fluids to manage ascites. Protein should be lowered if ammonia is high or should be raised if it's not.
	</liver-failure>

	<ascites>
		Abdominal skin is taut and glistening
	</ascites>

	<scabies>
		Transmission of scabies occurs through mites.
	</scabies>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Elevated T-waves
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hypocalcemia>
		tetany - spasms of hands, legs and feet, could also result in breating and cardio disturbances, overactive deep tendon reflexes, muscle twitching.
Chvostek sign - facial contraction when tapping on the facial nerve.
Trousseau sign - muscle scpasm of the hand and wrist when blood pressure cuff is applied.
Finger numbness.
	</hypocalcemia>

	<hyperthermia>
		Give acetaminophen and apply a cooling blanket.
	</hyperthermia>

	<hypocalcemia>
		Muscle cramps, Chvostek sign (facial nerve spasm), Trousseaue's sign (bp cuff dorsiflexion)
	</hypocalcemia>

	<hypercalcemia>
		Weakness, nausea, polyurea
	</hypercalcemia>

	<Hyperkalemia>
		Promotes reabsorption of hydrogen ions, leading to acidosis.
	</Hyperkalemia>

	<hypernatremia>
		Could be caused by diabetes-insipidus
	</hypernatremia>

	<Hypervolemia>
		Causes tachycardia.
	</Hypervolemia>

	<hypokalemia>
		Muscle weakness, especially in the legs. Parasthesia in the hands.
	</hypokalemia>

	<Alzheimers>
		Restlessness and pacing
	</Alzheimers>

	<hepatitis-a>
		Transmitted through a fecal-oral route.
Standard precautiuons are enough unless incontinent or diapered, then contact precautions are needed.
	</hepatitis-a>

	<hepatitis>
		Early symptoms are nausea and anorexia.
	</hepatitis>

	<hepatitis-a>
		Fecal-oral route.
Not transmitted through the blood.
Traveling to high to medium level affected couintries such as Africa, South America, and Asia.
	</hepatitis-a>

	<respiratory-rate>
		Normal is 12 and higher per minute
	</respiratory-rate>

	<newborn-respiratory-rate>
		Normal is 30 - 60 breaths per minute.
	</newborn-respiratory-rate>

	<urge-incontinence>
		Also called overactive bladder
Sudden urge to urinate with no control
Often due to damage to the nerves
	</urge-incontinence>

	<stress-urinary-incontinence>
		Release of urine when bladder is physically stressed (pressed) from physical activity, jumping, laughing, sneezing etc.
	</stress-urinary-incontinence>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Elevated T-waves
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Treatment is to administer insulin, insulin activates sodium-proton pump which pumps sodium ions in to the cell and hydrogen ions out, the influx of sodium activates the the sodium-potassium pump which job it's to maintain intracellular potassium concentrations higher and sodium concentrations lower. The Na-K pump exports 3 ions of sodium and imports two ions of potassium, lowering the overall serum potassium concentration.
Symptom is an elevated T wave
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hypocalcemia>
		Muscle cramps, Chvostek sign (facial nerve spasm), Trousseaue's sign (bp cuff dorsiflexion)
	</hypocalcemia>

	<hypercalcemia>
		Weakness, nausea, polyurea
	</hypercalcemia>

	<hyponatremia>
		Body compensates for low sodium by retaining lithium.
	</hyponatremia>

	<hypoglycemia>
		Blood glucose less than 60mg/dL
Treatments when concious - 15-20g of rapid acting sugars such as 4oz fruit juice or soda, 8 oz milk, tablespoon of sugar
Treatments when semiconcious - 1mg glucagon IM or SC or 25-50 mg 50% dextrose IV.
	</hypoglycemia>

	<hypokalemia>
		Muscle weakness, especially in the legs. Parasthesia in the hands.
	</hypokalemia>

	<tuberculosis>
		A diagnosis is confirmed when a sputum sample is cultured.
	</tuberculosis>

	<tuberculosis>
		Medications used: isoniazid, rifampin, pyrazinamide, ethambutol
	</tuberculosis>

	<tuberculosis>
		Endemic in certain parts of asia, people from Asian countries should be screened for it.
	</tuberculosis>

	<sickle-cell-crisis>
		Fluids are used to reduce blood viscosity
Activity is limited to reduce oxygen needs
Diet is used to promote metabolic demand, rich in calories and high in protein
Oxygen is atministed to prevent further cell sickling
Pain management should be done with a combination of opiod and nonopiod drugs, not just nonopioid, as pain could be severe
	</sickle-cell-crisis>

	<ascites>
		Abdominal skin is taut and glistening
	</ascites>

	<ascites>
		Pushes on the lungs, decreasing lung capacity
	</ascites>

	<escherichia-coli>
		Does not need contact precautions unless the client is incontinent or is wearing a diaper.
	</escherichia-coli>

	<hepatitis-a>
		Spread via fecal-oral route.
In pediatric clients symptoms are flu like in nature, including anorexia, fever, malaise, lethargy, clay colored stools, dark urine. Jaundice is not common in pediatric patients. 
Before age 6, 70% of patients will be asymptomatic.
	</hepatitis-a>

	<hepatitis>
		Early symptoms are nausea and anorexia.
	</hepatitis>

	<hepatitis-a>
		Fecal-oral route.
Not transmitted through the blood.
Traveling to high to medium level affected couintries such as Africa, South America, and Asia.
	</hepatitis-a>

	<neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>
		Complication resulting from antipsychotic medications
Could occur even with one dose of me\dissatisfaction, therefore must always monitor temperature when administering antipsychotics
	</neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>

	<neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>
		Life threatening reaction that is lethal in 10% of cases.
Stop the medication. Cool the body, administer bromocriptine to treat muscle regidity, dantrolene to reduce muscle spasms.
	</neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>

	<ibuprofen>
		Maximum daliy dosage: 3,200 mg/day
	</ibuprofen>

	<live-virus-vaccine>
		Vaccines for herpes zoster (shingles), measles vaccine and mumps vaccine.
	</live-virus-vaccine>

	<pregnancy-low-back-pain>
		Intermittened low back pain could indicate overly distended uterus and could be a sign of oncoming labor. Especially if there are multiple fetuses.
	</pregnancy-low-back-pain>

	<meningitis>
		Monitor for deterioration: decreased LOC, Cushing triad, impaired pupil reactivity to light.
	</meningitis>

	<tendonitis>
		Treatment is applying ice, resting and analgesics.
	</tendonitis>

	<meningitis>
		Fever, neck pain and stiffness, Headache
	</meningitis>

	<tendonitis>
		Treatment is applying ice, resting and analgesics.
	</tendonitis>

	<hepatitis>
		Early symptoms are nausea and anorexia.
	</hepatitis>

	<restraints>
		Before applying restraints check for co-occuring medical conditions that may contraindicate their use such as vomiting or seizures.
	</restraints>

	<hyperthermia>
		Give acetaminophen and apply a cooling blanket.
	</hyperthermia>

	<hyponatremia>
		Body compensates for low sodium by retaining lithium.
	</hyponatremia>

	<hypokalemia>
		Muscle weakness, especially in the legs. Parasthesia in the hands.
	</hypokalemia>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Elevated T-waves
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Treatment is to administer insulin, insulin activates sodium-proton pump which pumps sodium ions in to the cell and hydrogen ions out, the influx of sodium activates the the sodium-potassium pump which job it's to maintain intracellular potassium concentrations higher and sodium concentrations lower. The Na-K pump exports 3 ions of sodium and imports two ions of potassium, lowering the overall serum potassium concentration.
Symptom is an elevated T wave
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hypothermia>
		Shivering increases oxygen consumption.
	</hypothermia>

	<hypercalcemia>
		Weakness, nausea, polyurea
	</hypercalcemia>

	<hypernatremia>
		Could be caused by diabetes-insipidus
	</hypernatremia>

	<alcohol-withdrawal>
		Signs and symptoms: elevated temperature, nocturnal leg cramps, generalized muscle pain and malaise, tremors
	</alcohol-withdrawal>

	<opioid-withdrawl>
		shivering, abdominal cramping, muscle and bone pain, vomiting, diarrhea.
	</opioid-withdrawl>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Elevated T-waves
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Treatment is to administer insulin, insulin activates sodium-proton pump which pumps sodium ions in to the cell and hydrogen ions out, the influx of sodium activates the the sodium-potassium pump which job it's to maintain intracellular potassium concentrations higher and sodium concentrations lower. The Na-K pump exports 3 ions of sodium and imports two ions of potassium, lowering the overall serum potassium concentration.
Symptom is an elevated T wave
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hypocalcemia>
		tetany - spasms of hands, legs and feet, could also result in breating and cardio disturbances, overactive deep tendon reflexes, muscle twitching.
Chvostek sign - facial contraction when tapping on the facial nerve.
Trousseau sign - muscle scpasm of the hand and wrist when blood pressure cuff is applied.
Finger numbness.
	</hypocalcemia>

	<hypercalcemia>
		Weakness, nausea, polyurea
	</hypercalcemia>

	<hyponatremia>
		Body compensates for low sodium by retaining lithium.
	</hyponatremia>

	<hypoglycemia>
		Blood glucose less than 60mg/dL
Treatments when concious - 15-20g of rapid acting sugars such as 4oz fruit juice or soda, 8 oz milk, tablespoon of sugar
Treatments when semiconcious - 1mg glucagon IM or SC or 25-50 mg 50% dextrose IV.
	</hypoglycemia>

	<hypokalemia>
		Muscle weakness, especially in the legs. Parasthesia in the hands.
	</hypokalemia>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Elevated T-waves
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Treatment is to administer insulin, insulin activates sodium-proton pump which pumps sodium ions in to the cell and hydrogen ions out, the influx of sodium activates the the sodium-potassium pump which job it's to maintain intracellular potassium concentrations higher and sodium concentrations lower. The Na-K pump exports 3 ions of sodium and imports two ions of potassium, lowering the overall serum potassium concentration.
Symptom is an elevated T wave
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hypocalcemia>
		tetany - spasms of hands, legs and feet, could also result in breating and cardio disturbances, overactive deep tendon reflexes, muscle twitching.
Chvostek sign - facial contraction when tapping on the facial nerve.
Trousseau sign - muscle scpasm of the hand and wrist when blood pressure cuff is applied.
Finger numbness.
	</hypocalcemia>

	<hyperthermia>
		Give acetaminophen and apply a cooling blanket.
	</hyperthermia>

	<hypocalcemia>
		Muscle cramps, Chvostek sign (facial nerve spasm), Trousseaue's sign (bp cuff dorsiflexion)
	</hypocalcemia>

	<Hyperkalemia>
		Promotes reabsorption of hydrogen ions, leading to acidosis.
	</Hyperkalemia>

	<hypernatremia>
		Could be caused by diabetes-insipidus
	</hypernatremia>

	<hypoglycemia>
		Blood glucose less than 60mg/dL
Treatments when concious - 15-20g of rapid acting sugars such as 4oz fruit juice or soda, 8 oz milk, tablespoon of sugar
Treatments when semiconcious - 1mg glucagon IM or SC or 25-50 mg 50% dextrose IV.
	</hypoglycemia>

	<Hypervolemia>
		Causes tachycardia.
	</Hypervolemia>

	<hypokalemia>
		Muscle weakness, especially in the legs. Parasthesia in the hands.
	</hypokalemia>

	<restraints>
		Room where easily seen.
Food and water every 2 hours.
Monitor skin integrity every 30 mintues to monitor for redness. 
Toilet every 2 hours.
Range of motion for 10 min every 2 hours. 
Monitor every 15 min then every hour.
	</restraints>

	<alzheimer>
		Reduced anxiety first then reorient the client. 
Reduce anxiety by staying with the client and explaining the environment. 
Clients may be calmer in the morning and get more agitated as the day progresses.
	</alzheimer>

	<chronic-kidney-disease>
		Foods to avoid: citrus fruit, they are high in potassium as damaged kidneys cannot remove it. 
Dried fruits, avocado, tomato, potatoes and bananas. 
Calcium is lost through the damaged kidneys.
Dairy products are high in phosphorus which binds even more calcium and should be avoided.
Dietary protein incrases uric acid (urea) production which cannot be cleared by the damaged kidneys. Dietary protein should be kept at low or normal levels (but not incrased).
	</chronic-kidney-disease>

	<chronic-kidney-disease>
		Limit potassium and phosphorus.
	</chronic-kidney-disease>

	<chronic-kidney-disease>
		Diet needs to be low in protein, sodium, potassium and phosphorus.
	</chronic-kidney-disease>

	<phosphorus-rich-foods>
		Dairy products (except brie cheese, sherbet, cream cheese, ricotta cheese)
Whole wheat cereals, oatmeal, bran and granola
	</phosphorus-rich-foods>

	<chronic-kidney-disease>
		Foods to avoid: citrus fruit, they are high in potassium as damaged kidneys cannot remove it. 
Dried fruits, avocado, tomato, potatoes and bananas. 
Calcium is lost through the damaged kidneys.
Dairy products are high in phosphorus which binds even more calcium and should be avoided.
Dietary protein incrases uric acid (urea) production which cannot be cleared by the damaged kidneys. Dietary protein should be kept at low or normal levels (but not incrased).
	</chronic-kidney-disease>

	<chronic-kidney-disease>
		Diet includes increased calories, animal protein (not plant), low potassium, low phosphorus and low sodium, limit dairy to 1 cup of milk or 1 ounce of cheese per day (because of phosphorus limits)
	</chronic-kidney-disease>

	<chronic-kidney-disease>
		Diet needs to be low in protein, sodium, potassium and phosphorus.
	</chronic-kidney-disease>

	<potassium-rich-foods>
		Beets, oranges, melons, tomatoes, dried beans, cooked greens, brown rice, dairy, whole wheat bread
	</potassium-rich-foods>

	<lithium>
		Could decrease thyroid hormone(T4) secretion.
	</lithium>

	<neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>
		Life threatening idiosynchratic reaction to dopamine receptor-antagonist drugs.
Usually occurs 4-14 days after the start of therapy. 
Symptoms: sudden high fever, rigidity, tachycardia, hypertension, decreased level of consciousness. 
Bromocriptine should be administered, it counteracts the effects of dopamine antagonists.
	</neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>

	<neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>
		Life threatening reaction that is lethal in 10% of cases.
Stop the medication. Cool the body, administer bromocriptine to treat muscle regidity, dantrolene to reduce muscle spasms.
	</neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>

	<escherichia-coli>
		Transmitted by fecal-oral route, causes acute diarrhea.
Standard precautions are enough unless the client is incontinetn or is diapered, then contact precautions are needed.
	</escherichia-coli>

	<infant-respiratory-rate>
		Less then 66 breaths per minute (normal), if greater then tachypnea
	</infant-respiratory-rate>

	<newborn-respiratory-rate>
		Normal is 30 - 60 breaths per minute.
	</newborn-respiratory-rate>

	<Addisons-disease>
		Autoimmune disorders that results in destruction of adrenal glands. 
All three corticoids are reduced: glucocorticoids (cortisol), mineralcorticoids (aldosterone), and androgens. 
Lifelong steroid homrones given, doses should be increased during stresses like surgery.
Salt is added to the diet. 
Potassium is usually elevated.
	</Addisons-disease>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Elevated T-waves
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Treatment is to administer insulin, insulin activates sodium-proton pump which pumps sodium ions in to the cell and hydrogen ions out, the influx of sodium activates the the sodium-potassium pump which job it's to maintain intracellular potassium concentrations higher and sodium concentrations lower. The Na-K pump exports 3 ions of sodium and imports two ions of potassium, lowering the overall serum potassium concentration.
Symptom is an elevated T wave
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hypercalcemia>
		Weakness, nausea, polyurea
	</hypercalcemia>

	<hypernatremia>
		Could be caused by diabetes-insipidus
	</hypernatremia>

	<Hypervolemia>
		Causes tachycardia.
	</Hypervolemia>

	<hypokalemia>
		Muscle weakness, especially in the legs. Parasthesia in the hands.
	</hypokalemia>

	<colorectal-cancer>
		Risk factors: obesity, smoking, alcohol, physical inactivity and diet.
Other risk factors: Age (45+), Race(African-American and Eastern Jewish), Type II Diabetes
	</colorectal-cancer>

	<lithium>
		Expected side effects - fine hand tremor, polyuria and polydypsia. 
Maintaince dose is reached after 7-14 days.
	</lithium>

	<hypocalcemia>
		tetany - spasms of hands, legs and feet, could also result in breating and cardio disturbances, overactive deep tendon reflexes, muscle twitching.
Chvostek sign - facial contraction when tapping on the facial nerve.
Trousseau sign - muscle scpasm of the hand and wrist when blood pressure cuff is applied.
Finger numbness.
	</hypocalcemia>

	<hypothermia>
		Shivering increases oxygen consumption.
	</hypothermia>

	<hypocalcemia>
		Muscle cramps, Chvostek sign (facial nerve spasm), Trousseaue's sign (bp cuff dorsiflexion)
	</hypocalcemia>

	<hypernatremia>
		Could be caused by diabetes-insipidus
	</hypernatremia>

	<hypokalemia>
		Muscle weakness, especially in the legs. Parasthesia in the hands.
	</hypokalemia>

	<corticosteroid>
		Increases levels of glucose, increases sodium levels, decreases potassium and calcium levels
	</corticosteroid>

	<tuberculosis>
		Transporting - a patient with TB should be wearing a surgical mask (not N95) and the persons caring for them should be alerted and wear N95.
	</tuberculosis>

	<tuberculosis>
		Medications used: isoniazid, rifampin, pyrazinamide, ethambutol
	</tuberculosis>

	<tuberculosis>
		Endemic in certain parts of asia, people from Asian countries should be screened for it.
	</tuberculosis>

	<live-vaccines>
		Measles, mumps, rubella (MMR), varicella (chicken pox), small pox, rotavirus, influenza.
Should not be given to pregnant women, vaccinate in postpartum period, because of the theoretical risk of tranmission to the fetus. 
Influenza vaccines are recommended if pregnant during the influenza season. 
Inactivated vaccines such as influenza, tetanus, hep B could be given.
	</live-vaccines>

	<peripherally-inserted-central-catheter>
		Clean around the catheter in circular motion and away.
Dressing changes require sterile technique
Old dressing should be removed toward the insertion site.
Change gloves after removing the old dressing.
	</peripherally-inserted-central-catheter>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Elevated T-waves
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Treatment is to administer insulin, insulin activates sodium-proton pump which pumps sodium ions in to the cell and hydrogen ions out, the influx of sodium activates the the sodium-potassium pump which job it's to maintain intracellular potassium concentrations higher and sodium concentrations lower. The Na-K pump exports 3 ions of sodium and imports two ions of potassium, lowering the overall serum potassium concentration.
Symptom is an elevated T wave
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hyperthermia>
		Give acetaminophen and apply a cooling blanket.
	</hyperthermia>

	<hypercalcemia>
		Weakness, nausea, polyurea
	</hypercalcemia>

	<Hyperkalemia>
		Promotes reabsorption of hydrogen ions, leading to acidosis.
	</Hyperkalemia>

	<hyponatremia>
		Body compensates for low sodium by retaining lithium.
	</hyponatremia>

	<left-hemisphere>
		Controls speech, math skills and analytical thinking.
	</left-hemisphere>

	<right-hemisphere>
		Responsible for identifying person, place and times.
Responsible for controlling impulsive behaviour.
	</right-hemisphere>

	<chronic-kidney-disease>
		Foods to avoid: citrus fruit, they are high in potassium as damaged kidneys cannot remove it. 
Dried fruits, avocado, tomato, potatoes and bananas. 
Calcium is lost through the damaged kidneys.
Dairy products are high in phosphorus which binds even more calcium and should be avoided.
Dietary protein incrases uric acid (urea) production which cannot be cleared by the damaged kidneys. Dietary protein should be kept at low or normal levels (but not incrased).
	</chronic-kidney-disease>

	<chronic-kidney-disease>
		Diet includes increased calories, animal protein (not plant), low potassium, low phosphorus and low sodium, limit dairy to 1 cup of milk or 1 ounce of cheese per day (because of phosphorus limits)
	</chronic-kidney-disease>

	<chronic-kidney-disease>
		Limit potassium and phosphorus.
	</chronic-kidney-disease>

	<hypocalcemia>
		tetany - spasms of hands, legs and feet, could also result in breating and cardio disturbances, overactive deep tendon reflexes, muscle twitching.
Chvostek sign - facial contraction when tapping on the facial nerve.
Trousseau sign - muscle scpasm of the hand and wrist when blood pressure cuff is applied.
Finger numbness.
	</hypocalcemia>

	<hypocalcemia>
		Muscle cramps, Chvostek sign (facial nerve spasm), Trousseaue's sign (bp cuff dorsiflexion)
	</hypocalcemia>

	<hypercalcemia>
		Weakness, nausea, polyurea
	</hypercalcemia>

	<hypokalemia>
		Muscle weakness, especially in the legs. Parasthesia in the hands.
	</hypokalemia>

	<cataracts>
		After surgery: avoid increasing IOP, avoid sleeping on affected side, wear an eye patch at night and glasses durinig the day, avoid getting water in the eye, avoid prolonged reading or eye strain.
	</cataracts>

	<liver-failure>
		Underproduction of bicarbonate leads to metabolic-acidosis
	</liver-failure>

	<sterile-field>
		Situations where sterile field is required: dialysis catheters, chest tube insertion, inserting central venous or arterial lines, inserting drainage devices.
	</sterile-field>

	<peripherally-inserted-central-catheter>
		In case the catheter breaks, tourniquet the arm by the shoulder - then check to make sure the arm still has a radial pulse (don't want to complete occlude the blood flow), then order an x-ray.
Do not move the client to prevent movement of the catheter piece.
	</peripherally-inserted-central-catheter>

	<hepatitis-a>
		Spread via fecal-oral route.
In pediatric clients symptoms are flu like in nature, including anorexia, fever, malaise, lethargy, clay colored stools, dark urine. Jaundice is not common in pediatric patients. 
Before age 6, 70% of patients will be asymptomatic.
	</hepatitis-a>

	<hepatitis-a>
		Transmitted through a fecal-oral route.
Standard precautiuons are enough unless incontinent or diapered, then contact precautions are needed.
	</hepatitis-a>

	<mastitis>
		Blocked duct due to bacterial infection, causes reddned inflamed painful breast. 
Treated with antibiotics. 
Cracked nipples.
Risk factor is poor hygine.
Failure to empty while breastfeeding.
	</mastitis>

	<hepatitis-a>
		Fecal-oral route.
Not transmitted through the blood.
Traveling to high to medium level affected couintries such as Africa, South America, and Asia.
	</hepatitis-a>

	<tuberculosis>
		Transporting - a patient with TB should be wearing a surgical mask (not N95) and the persons caring for them should be alerted and wear N95.
	</tuberculosis>

	<tuberculosis>
		A diagnosis is confirmed when a sputum sample is cultured.
	</tuberculosis>

	<tuberculosis>
		Endemic in certain parts of asia, people from Asian countries should be screened for it.
	</tuberculosis>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Elevated T-waves
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Treatment is to administer insulin, insulin activates sodium-proton pump which pumps sodium ions in to the cell and hydrogen ions out, the influx of sodium activates the the sodium-potassium pump which job it's to maintain intracellular potassium concentrations higher and sodium concentrations lower. The Na-K pump exports 3 ions of sodium and imports two ions of potassium, lowering the overall serum potassium concentration.
Symptom is an elevated T wave
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hypercalcemia>
		Weakness, nausea, polyurea
	</hypercalcemia>

	<Hyperkalemia>
		Promotes reabsorption of hydrogen ions, leading to acidosis.
	</Hyperkalemia>

	<sterile-field>
		Keep hands at or above table level
1in edge of the sterile field is non sterile and could only be touched with clean golve (not sterile glove)
	</sterile-field>

	<colostomy>
		Rinsing or reusing the ostomy pouch is not recommended. 
Do not reduce fluid intake to make the stool harder.
	</colostomy>

	<dialysis>
		Administering an antihypertensive prior to could lead to hypotension, the nurse should wait until after dialysis to administer it.
Antimicrobials and antibiotics are removed with the dialysate solution, should be withheld until after.
	</dialysis>

	<neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>
		Life threatening idiosynchratic reaction to dopamine receptor-antagonist drugs.
Usually occurs 4-14 days after the start of therapy. 
Symptoms: sudden high fever, rigidity, tachycardia, hypertension, decreased level of consciousness. 
Bromocriptine should be administered, it counteracts the effects of dopamine antagonists.
	</neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>

	<neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>
		Complication resulting from antipsychotic medications
Could occur even with one dose of me\dissatisfaction, therefore must always monitor temperature when administering antipsychotics
	</neuroleptic-malignant-syndrome>

	<Addisons-disease>
		Hyposecrion of adrenal hormones
Causes hyponatremia, hypotension, fatigue and muscle cramps
Hyperkalemia due to decreased potassium release
Could result in hypercalcemia
Tanned skin without sun exposure
Hairloss due to reduced androgen levels, especially in females because adrenals produce most androgens in females
Hypoglycemia due to reduction of cortisol
Gastric acid production decreases
	</Addisons-disease>

	<multiple-sclerosis>
		treatment is with beta interferon
	</multiple-sclerosis>

	<alcohol-withdrawal>
		Signs and symptoms: elevated temperature, nocturnal leg cramps, generalized muscle pain and malaise, tremors
	</alcohol-withdrawal>

	<alcohol-withdrawal>
		Symptoms occur 4-6 hours after last drink and last up to 14 days.
Treatment is to use benzodiazepines to alleviate the agitation. 
Common benzodiazapeine to use is chlordiazepoxide. 
Symtpoms - tremor, insomnia, dilated pupils, tachycardia, perspiration, hallucinations.
	</alcohol-withdrawal>

	<squamous-cell-carcinoma>
		Firm nodular lesion covered by crust.
	</squamous-cell-carcinoma>

	<basal-cell-carcinoma>
		Most common type of skin cancer.
Most are located on face and neck.
Sometimes donut shaped pearly papule with a waxy border.
Most are localized and do not metastasize.
	</basal-cell-carcinoma>

	<infant-respiratory-rate>
		Less then 66 breaths per minute (normal), if greater then tachypnea
	</infant-respiratory-rate>

	<respiratory-rate>
		Normal is 12 and higher per minute
	</respiratory-rate>

	<low-back-pain>
		Don't straing to reach for things.
Do not lie in prone position.
Avoid knee and hip extension.
	</low-back-pain>

	<meningitis>
		Fever, neck pain and stiffness, Headache
	</meningitis>

	<meningitis>
		Monitor for deterioration: decreased LOC, Cushing triad, impaired pupil reactivity to light.
	</meningitis>

	<colorectal-cancer>
		Risk factors - African American, BMI &gt; 30, smoking, alcohol consumption &gt; 4 drinks per week, red meat &gt; 7 servings per week, relatives with the disease 
When considering who is at higher risk, count the risk factors
	</colorectal-cancer>

	<urinary-incontinence>
		Toilet schedule - voiding every 2 hours
Stress incontinence - occurs when abdominal pressure increases due to sneezing, laughter etc. 
Urge incontinence - occurs after experience sudden urge to void, with an inability to suppress urination before reaching bathroom.
	</urinary-incontinence>

	<urinary-incontinence>
		Toilet schedule - voiding every 2 hours
Stress incontinence - occurs when abdominal pressure increases due to sneezing, laughter etc. 
Urge incontinence - occurs after experience sudden urge to void, with an inability to suppress urination before reaching bathroom.
	</urinary-incontinence>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Elevated T-waves
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hyperkalemia>
		Treatment is to administer insulin, insulin activates sodium-proton pump which pumps sodium ions in to the cell and hydrogen ions out, the influx of sodium activates the the sodium-potassium pump which job it's to maintain intracellular potassium concentrations higher and sodium concentrations lower. The Na-K pump exports 3 ions of sodium and imports two ions of potassium, lowering the overall serum potassium concentration.
Symptom is an elevated T wave
	</hyperkalemia>

	<hypocalcemia>
		tetany - spasms of hands, legs and feet, could also result in breating and cardio disturbances, overactive deep tendon reflexes, muscle twitching.
Chvostek sign - facial contraction when tapping on the facial nerve.
Trousseau sign - muscle scpasm of the hand and wrist when blood pressure cuff is applied.
Finger numbness.
	</hypocalcemia>

	<hypothermia>
		Shivering increases oxygen consumption.
	</hypothermia>

	<hypocalcemia>
		Muscle cramps, Chvostek sign (facial nerve spasm), Trousseaue's sign (bp cuff dorsiflexion)
	</hypocalcemia>

	<hypercalcemia>
		Weakness, nausea, polyurea
	</hypercalcemia>

	<Hyperkalemia>
		Promotes reabsorption of hydrogen ions, leading to acidosis.
	</Hyperkalemia>

	<hyponatremia>
		Body compensates for low sodium by retaining lithium.
	</hyponatremia>

	<hypoglycemia>
		Blood glucose less than 60mg/dL
Treatments when concious - 15-20g of rapid acting sugars such as 4oz fruit juice or soda, 8 oz milk, tablespoon of sugar
Treatments when semiconcious - 1mg glucagon IM or SC or 25-50 mg 50% dextrose IV.
	</hypoglycemia>

	<tuberculosis>
		Transporting - a patient with TB should be wearing a surgical mask (not N95) and the persons caring for them should be alerted and wear N95.
	</tuberculosis>

	<tuberculosis>
		A diagnosis is confirmed when a sputum sample is cultured.
	</tuberculosis>

	<tuberculosis>
		Medications used: isoniazid, rifampin, pyrazinamide, ethambutol
	</tuberculosis>

	<iliostomy>
		If constipated then massage around the stoma prmoting peristalsis, drink warm fluids they promote peristalsis and provide a mild cathartic effect, take a warm shower which helps promote abdominal muscle relaxation
	</iliostomy>

	<cataract>
		After surgery: avoid activitives that increase IOP such as bending or lifting heavy equipment (more than 10-15lbs)
	</cataract>

	<hepatitis-a>
		Spread via fecal-oral route.
In pediatric clients symptoms are flu like in nature, including anorexia, fever, malaise, lethargy, clay colored stools, dark urine. Jaundice is not common in pediatric patients. 
Before age 6, 70% of patients will be asymptomatic.
	</hepatitis-a>

	<hepatitis-a>
		Transmitted through a fecal-oral route.
Standard precautiuons are enough unless incontinent or diapered, then contact precautions are needed.
	</hepatitis-a>

	<hepatitis>
		Early symptoms are nausea and anorexia.
	</hepatitis>

</empty>

